<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christ's importunity with sinners to accept of him by S. Bold.</title>
            <author>Bold, S. (Samuel), 1649-1737.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 165 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 80 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28583</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3478</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26454</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09471163</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09471163</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43210</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28583)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43210)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1302:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christ's importunity with sinners to accept of him by S. Bold.</title>
                  <author>Bold, S. (Samuel), 1649-1737.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 139 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Awnsham Churchill and are to be sold by William Churchill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Repentance.</term>
               <term>Salvation.</term>
               <term>Forgiveness of sin.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43210:1"/>
            <p>CHRIST's IMPORTUNITY WITH SINNERS To accept of HIM.</p>
            <p>By <hi>S. Bold,</hi> Rector of <hi>Steple, Dorſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>All day long have I ſtretched forth my hands unto a diſobedient and gainſaying People. <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 10.21.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>As I live, ſaith the Lord God, I have no pleaſure in the death of the Wicked, but that the Wicked turn from his way and live: Turn ye, turn ye from your evil ways; for why will ye die? <bibl>
                  <hi>Ezek. 3.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Awnſham Churchill</hi> in <hi>Ave-Mary</hi> Lane, and are to be ſold by <hi>William Churchill</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter.</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:43210:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43210:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Happineſs and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Heaven, and the Horror and Anguiſh of Hell, are moſt certain, ſtable, and durable Eſtates. We have as great, as convincing, and as ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:43210:3"/>Evidence, that wicked, ungodly, and impenitent Sinners, ſhall be for ever inexpreſsibly and unconceivably miſerable, as is fit for reaſonable Creatures to have in this World, and as Infinite Wiſdom hath thought meet to afford. The Evidence is ſuch, that whoſoever would pretend to require more ſuitable, more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and more powerful diſcoveries, were he put to invent Methods of his own for his particular fatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, would have as reaſonable, as juſt, and as good grounds, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Humour and Fancy were gratified, to continue an Infidel as before; ſee <hi>Luke 16.30, 31.</hi> He that thinks it a diſparagement to his Wit, or a blemiſh to his Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, to acquieſce in the Teſtimony
<pb facs="tcp:43210:3"/>of God, as delivered in our Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, might with greater aſſurance refuſe his aſſent to the Damn'd themſelves, did he ſee them in Flames, and hear their perſonal ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments, that their Vices and Sins had wrought them all that miſery. For why ſhould he heed and credit them who have not trick enough to diſguiſe, or obſtinacy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to deny their Guilt.</p>
            <p>The ſubſequent Diſcourſe was not deſign'd for them whoſe unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Immoralities, or ſtudied In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulity, has given them an ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation (as they conceit) above con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction. If nothing but particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Experience, will aſſure them of eternal and unſufferable Torments,
<pb facs="tcp:43210:4"/>I leave them (as Perſons out of the reach of Ratiocination and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe) to what will certainly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertake them, and that before they are willing.</p>
            <p>And therefore intending the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Diſcourſe, eſpecially for the plain and ordinary ſort, who have not loſt all ſenſe, I will briefly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs to them in a Stile proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the plainneſs and familiarity uſed in the Diſcourſe it ſelf.</p>
            <p>I entreat you, who retain any ſparks of Humanity, who have a ſenſe that your Souls are Immortal, who acknowledg there is ſome dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between Good and Evil, Virtue and Vice, and whom your
<pb facs="tcp:43210:4"/>general Profeſsion do own that the Scriptures are the Word of God; I ſay, I do beg, and moſt earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſeech you, by all that ſhould be dear and precious unto you, to think ſeriouſly a little on the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Particulars. Be ſo juſt to your ſelves, ſo reſpectful to your Maker, ſo civil and kind to them who do moſt paſsionately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire your everlaſting Happineſs, as to allow a few ſober thoughts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Matters which be of moſt neceſſary and unſpeakable impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance unto you. Why ſhould you ruſh upon God's Wrath, precipita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and heedleſly throw your ſelves headlong into unquenchable Burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and grieve and wound the
<pb facs="tcp:43210:5"/>Hearts of thoſe who inceſſantly pray, and deſire, and long, and wait, for your endleſs Good and Comfort. Be prevailed with then to conſider, with ſome ſedateneſs and calmneſs, theſe few Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1. Though God made Man at firſt a very excellent, holy, upright, and unblemiſh'd Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yet now we are all by Sin defiled, and made unholy, and brought under Guilt. So that as long as we remain in our natural and unregenerate Eſtate, we are obnoxious and liable to God's Curſe, and have a juſt right to all the terrible
<pb facs="tcp:43210:5"/>Diſcoveries, and moſt dreadful Effects of Divine and Infinite Juſtice; ſee</hi> Rom. <hi>5.12. &amp; 1.18.</hi> Epheſ. <hi>2.1, 2, 3.</hi> John <hi>3.36.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2. God hath not left us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medileſly in that ſad and deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and as to all meer Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-relief, helpleſs Eſtate, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which we are ſunk by Sin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: But of his abundant rich and free Grace, He hath provided us an Alſufficient Saviour and Redeemer, and hath opened unto us a Door of Hope. He hath given his own Son to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume our Nature, and to make Peace and Reconciliation for us. By and through this Son of God, Pardon, Peace, and
<pb facs="tcp:43210:6"/>Mercy, deliverance from Sin Guilt, Miſery, and Eterna Damnation is to be obtained, and no other way; ſee</hi> Rom. <hi>5.8, 9, 10. 1</hi> Tim. <hi>1.15.</hi> Gal <hi>4.4, 5. 1</hi> John <hi>2.1, 2.</hi> Act. <hi>4.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3. The Lord Jeſus Chriſt having accompliſhed all that Work he undertook, and which was appointed him to finiſh upon Earth; and being entred into his glorious Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, doth make moſt gracious Offers of himſelf, his Love, his Mercy, his Spirit, and Benefits, unto poor Sinners, and is very importunate with them to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain and accept of the ſame;</hi> Epheſ. <hi>4.7, to 14.</hi> Act. <hi>13.26. 2</hi> Cor. <hi>5.19, to the end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb facs="tcp:43210:6"/>
               <hi>4. Multitudes who have the Goſpel, and partake of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of the Word, and make a profeſſion of Religion, and have theſe gracious Offers made unto them, do not ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly entertain, but deſpiſe and reject Chriſt and his Benefits. They ſtubbornly refuſe to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to his Authority, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with his Terms, and imploy themſelves in his Service. Nay, many offer him the greateſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes and contempt they can deviſe; ſee</hi> Mat. <hi>22.1, 2, &amp;c.</hi> Luke <hi>19.14.</hi> John <hi>5.40.</hi> Act. <hi>13.46. And do not the Lives and Practices of multitudes profeſſing Chriſtianity, demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate all this? Look into your
<pb facs="tcp:43210:7"/>Hearts, and examine the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary courſe of your Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Shall you not there find ſufficient and full proof, that hitherto you have rejected him? That yet he hath no room in your Hearts, no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences on your Practices! O, what Ignorance, what Rancor, Malice, Revenge, Hatred, Wrath, unmortified powerful Luſts; what Covetouſneſs, Earthly-mindedneſs, Carnality, Pride, Hypocriſy; what back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting, lying, ſlandering, evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeaking, prophane and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Swearing, vain, frothy, fooliſh, unedifying Words and Diſcourſe; what common conſtant neglect of the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb facs="tcp:43210:7"/>and Service of God, in Families, and in Private. What ſleighting and contemning God's Word and Ordinances! nay, what ridiculing, and mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſport of all ſerious Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion! what Drunkenneſs and Whoredom, Intemperance and Wantonneſs, Oppreſſion, Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Violence, and innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble other moſt notorious and abominable wickedneſſes, may multitudes of pretended Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians every where obſerve in, and juſtly charge themſelves with? Now, are theſe the Fruits of Chriſt's gracious and holy Preſence! Was Chriſt of ſuch a Mind! Did He do ſuch Things! Does he any where
<pb facs="tcp:43210:8"/>countenance and allow of ſuch things? Can thoſe Hearts which cheriſh ſuch Luſts, and from which ſuch polluted ſtreams, and corrupt Fruits do proceed, be a Temple for the Holy Jeſus to dwell in? Are not theſe the Fruits of the Fleſh, which ſhut the Heart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt, and exclude thoſe who cheriſh and practiſe them out of the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven?</hi> Gal. <hi>5.19, 20, 21.</hi> Rev. <hi>21.8. 1</hi> Cor. <hi>6.9, 10.</hi> Epheſ. <hi>4.29, 31.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5. All thoſe who enjoying the Goſpel, do ſtubbornly and finally reject Chriſt, and his gracious Offers, as their Guilt
<pb facs="tcp:43210:8"/>doth unmeaſurably exceed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Peoples, who have not the Light and Means, the Calls and Offers they have, ſo they may juſtly expect, that their Damnation, Miſery, and Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, will exceedingly out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weigh, and be increaſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond other Peoples. O, Sirs, who can think of your Danger, your Miſery, that dreadful Portion which is in ſtore for you, without Tears and Groans, without Trembling and Faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Heart and Soul? read with attention</hi> Prov. <hi>1.24, &amp;c.</hi> Heb. <hi>12.25.</hi> Matth. <hi>11.21, to 25.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb facs="tcp:43210:9"/>
               <hi>6. Thoſe who do truly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and entertain Chriſt, and cloſe with his gracious Offers, are very much changed and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered from what they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were, and all are by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. It is not a change of Name, or a change of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, or a change from a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or a change as to any thing which is purely External, which will ſerve turn to prove, that you have indeed cloſed with Chriſt. It muſt be a real change of the Heart, a change of Principles, of Ends, and Purpoſes, a change of the whole bent and exerciſe of all the Faculties and Powers of
<pb facs="tcp:43210:9"/>the Soul, and a change of Life, and courſe of Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. He that truly receives Chriſt, loves him with all his Heart, gives him the prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence in every thing, delights in his Laws, reſigns up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf entirely to his Diſpoſal and Government, depends and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies on his Merits, Alſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and Faithfulneſs, rejoices in his Comforts, and acquieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in a patient expectation of his coming, and the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of his Promiſes:</hi> Gal. <hi>6.14, 15. 2</hi> Cor. <hi>5.17.</hi> Rom. <hi>8.8, 9.</hi> Tit. <hi>2.11, 12, 13, 14.</hi> Tit. <hi>3.4, to 9.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:43210:10"/>
            <p>Now do you think on theſe things ſeriouſly, eſpecially exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, ſearch and conſider diligently the Scriptures you are referr'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and apply them faithfully and impartially to your own Conſciences and Lives. Make no delay, ſtand not out in oppoſing Chriſt any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Do not deceive and flatter your own Souls. Remember that God is True, and Faithful, and Juſt. That the Blood, and Love, and calls of Chriſt, will not be loſt; but if they be not carefully improved and cloſed with, they will bring Vengeance upon you to the uttermoſt. Remember that Chriſt's Invitations and Intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties will not be very much longer
<pb facs="tcp:43210:10"/>continued unto you. It will not be long before you muſt lie down in the Duſt, 'twill be but a little time more that you ſhall hear theſe Calls and Intreaties. In a little while you will be paſt reading the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, hearing Sermons, having Opportunities to cry and pray for Mercy and Grace with Hope. O, how fearful will your Eſtate be, if you reſist all Christ's Calls to accept of Him and Grace, till he withdraws himſelf in anger, and reſolves he will never ſpeak a word more of Peace or Incouragement unto you, or entertain a favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thought towards you? You muſt before long, quit all you ſet your Hearts on here; Riches, Applauſe, carnal Delights, Sports and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments,
<pb facs="tcp:43210:11"/>will in ſhort time take their leave, and fly away from you. Alas, get what you can here, if you are without Chriſt, you are miſerable, comfortleſs, helpleſs. E're long you will ſee Death, and Judgment, and Hell, plainly before you; now, what will relieve and ſupport you then? O what Trifles, what Torments will your Luſts, and all worldly Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Entertainments appear and be then? What will you do, if you perſist to deny Chriſt admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, when the Lord Jeſus ſhall come in flaming Fire, <hi>&amp;c. 2 Theſſ. 1.7, 8, 9.</hi> O what a dreadful Spectacle will Chriſt in Glory be, to all the obſtinate Deſpiſers, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners, and Sleighters of Him,
<pb facs="tcp:43210:11"/>his Grace, his Spirit, his Word, his Ordinances, his People, his Meſſengers? How full of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, amazement, and terror, will the appearance of Chriſt be, to all thoſe againſt whom his Blood will riſe, and plead for Vengeance? Preſs theſe things on your own Hearts, ſhew ſome love now at laſt to your own Souls. Build not your Hopes and Confidence on your belonging to any Congregation or Party, nor on the enjoyment of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Goſpel-priviledges; but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten to Chriſt indeed, and never be at reſt till ſavingly united unto him. Do not only read but practiſe good Books; <hi>Be not only hearers, but doers of the Word, leſt you deceive your own Souls,</hi> Jam.
<pb facs="tcp:43210:12"/>
               <hi>1.22.</hi> If you get any good by this Diſcourſe, give God all the Praiſe and Glory. And when you have got an intereſt in Chriſt, make uſe of it at the Throne of Grace; not only for your ſelf, but to further the ſpiritual Happineſs, and eternal Salvation of him, who earneſtly deſires and prays for your everlaſting Walfare,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43210:12"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>REVEL. iii. 20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Behold, I ſtand at the Door, and knock: if any Man hear my Voice, and open the Door, I will come into him, and will ſup with him, and he with me.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Condeſcention of our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour to poor Sinners, is very extraordinary and miraculous. That reiterated Affronts, and multiplied Provocations, do (as it were) but only lengthen out his Patience, and add warmth and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs to his Importunity, is indeed the higheſt demonſtration imaginable of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhing Kindneſs, and a Love which cannot be parallel'd.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:43210:13"/>
            <p>But this is not to encourage our Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy and Refractorineſs; It ſhould overcome our Sturdineſs, and conquer and maſter our Stubborneſs; it ſhould ſoften and make us tractable and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliant. O the hardneſs of that Heart, the ſearedneſs of that Soul and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which will not be melted into a remorſe for Sin, and a joyful unfeigned cloſure, with the Offers of Salvation and Mercy, at the earneſt Entreaties, and paſſionate Courtings of the Eternal and Almighty God! <hi>What ſhall we ſay then? ſhall we continue in Sin, becauſe Grace doth abound? God forbid.</hi> (Rom. 6.1, 2.) How ſhall we, who are thus ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited from Heaven, thus importuned by the Bleſſed Jeſus, live any longer in a contradiction unto him?</p>
            <p>The Love and Condeſcention of Chriſt is ſuch, and doth ſo eminently appear in many Inſtances, eſpecially in theſe mentioned in the Text, our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour himſelf ſeems to be almoſt tranſported at the conſideration of the ſame. That the Son of God, <hi>who thought it no robbery to be equal with God,</hi> ſhould take ſuch notice of Enemies, forlorn, deſpicable Wretches, miſerable Sinners
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43210:13"/>(who at beſt, whilſt in their natural Eſtate, can lay claim to nothing but Wrath and Damnation) as to ſtand before them, come unto them, and uſe all manner of earneſtneſs with them, to prevail with them to yield him admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance into their Hearts; that by this means they may be advanced, and have Communion and Fellowſhip with him, is ſo ſtrange, ſo unheard of a piece of Condeſcention, ſo wonderful, ſo ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing, ſo amazing an Inſtance of Love, our Saviour himſelf, at the mentioning of it, ſeems to be in a kind of rapture. He doth Preface it with a Note of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration. <hi>Behold!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we ſhould look upon it as a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Condeſcention in a great Prince or Emperor, to deſcend from his Throne, and come perſonally to viſit ſome poor Subject, who has no habitation or place of Aboad, but ſome ſmall weather-beaten crazy Cottage; nay, to viſit ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous Rebel, juſtly confined to a Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, covered with naſtineſs and filth; and there importune and entreat this miſerable Wretch to be reconciled unto him, that they may both dwell toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and mutually rejoice in each others
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43210:14"/>ſociety; What ought we then to think of our Bleſſed Saviour's ſoliciting and entreating, with the greateſt earneſtneſs, for admittance into our Hearts?</p>
            <p>We may take notice of two general Parts in the words.</p>
            <p n="1">I. The main ſubſtance of the Verſe, which conſiſts of two parts. 1. Our Saviour's earneſtneſs to be admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Sinner's Hearts; <hi>I ſtand at the Door and knock,</hi> &amp;c. 2. The Priviledges and Satisfaction conſequent upon our receiving of him; <hi>I will come in to him,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The way and manner how all this is commended to our conſideration, <hi>Behold!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I intend to ſay but little of this latter; and therefore as it ſtands firſt in the Text, ſo it ſhall immediately come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our conſideration.</p>
            <p>This word, <hi>Behold,</hi> noteth, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing follows which is of weight, and deſerves to be obſerved. Indeed it would greatly become and profit us, to take a particular and diſtinct notice of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43210:14"/>thoſe places of the Holy Scripture, which are thus ſolemnly recommended to our conſideration. For God certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſt knows what is of greateſt uſe for us: And to ſuffer ſuch Paſſages to ſlip our obſervation, without a diligent heedful attendance to them, which he hath ſet ſuch a Mark upon, and points out ſo carefully to our ſtudy, argues much diſregard to his Wiſdom and Goodneſs, and that our Religion is very weak and unoperative.</p>
            <p>You may more particularly take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that this word, <hi>Behold,</hi> hath three ſpecial ſignifications in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; or there are three ſeveral ends and purpoſes why it is uſed in the Scriptures.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is a <hi>Behold</hi> of Caution: To warn us to take heed of what will be extreamly hurtful and injurious to our Souls. John 5.14. <hi>Behold, thou art made whole: ſin no more, leſt a worſe thing come unto thee.</hi> God has done very much for thee, and ſignally holpen thee and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered thee; take care thou do not wilfully provoke him again, leſt he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict thee worſe, leſt thou be hardened in thy Sins, and Divine Wrath come
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43210:15"/>upon thee to the uttermoſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A <hi>Behold</hi> of Admiration! Which calls us to wonder and admire, with all the Powers of our Soul, at the exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Riches of Divine Goodneſs and Grace. 1 John 3.1. <hi>Behold, what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Love the Father hath beſtowed upon us, that we ſhould be called the Sons of God!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. A <hi>Behold,</hi> deſigned to excite and ſtir us up to take notice of ſome impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Matter ſpeedily, and to improve it without delay. 2 Cor. 6.2. <hi>Behold, now is the accepted time, behold, now is the day of Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This word, here in the Text, may have all theſe Significations attributed to it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As deſigned to admoniſh us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt reſiſting Chriſt any longer, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he hath ſtood ſo long, and urged us to give him admittance, leſt if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to keep our Hearts lock'd and barr'd againſt him, he ſhould depart from us in diſpleaſure, and never make us another offer of his Love and Grace. O how fearful a thing is it to ſend Chriſt away grieved and enraged, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of our final perverſneſs and ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borneſs,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43210:15"/>after he hath been long woing and perſwading us to accept of him and his Benefits!</p>
            <p n="2">2. As repreſenting to us how great, how wonderful, how unexpected an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Love Chriſt is pleaſed to vouchſafe us. What greater Love can Chriſt expreſs and ſhew to you than this? He experienced and met with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hard and injurious uſage here on Earth; He underwent many afflicting grievous pains; He ſuffered a very infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous tormenting kind of Death. He endured for Sinners infinitely more than we can conceive, yet did not all this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay and cool his Affection, he loves us ſtill, with a Love as ſtrong as ever. What Love is this! Love ſtronger than Death, Love that the Floods cannot drown; Love, which neither Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, nor Death, nor Life, nor Glory, can overcome. Here is room indeed for our admiration and wonder; ceaſe then your wondering at other things, which ſeem ſtrange and unuſual, they are all nothing, if compared with this Love of Chriſt. Let all your admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion center here, on this fathomleſs, this infinite, incomprehenſible, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43210:16"/>Object of it. What can we juſtly wonder at, beſides the infinite Riches of our Saviour's Love and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcention, unleſs at that horrible and aſtoniſhing Prodigy, that People ſhould be ſo inſenſible, ſottiſh, and ſturdy, as to ſlight, neglect, and deſpiſe all the exceeding abundance of the Riches of Divine Grace and Kindneſs?</p>
            <p n="3">3. As exciting and ſtirring us up to take notice of our dear Saviour; and with what tenderneſs and condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he carries himſelf towards us. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, thy Saviour doth ſtand without, and has been long waiting on thee, and doth ſtill entreat thee earneſtly to give him admittance. O take notice how the King of Glory is come to viſit thee! and is deſirous to have communion with thee! Behold, Salvation is now come to thy Houſe; and what! wilt thou deny reception to, and ſhut thy Doors againſt ſuch a Gueſt?</p>
            <p>We may fairly enough furniſh our ſelves with this Inſtruction from this word, <hi>Behold,</hi> as uſed in this place, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Love to poor Sinners, is a Truth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43210:16"/>of extraordinary importance, and ſhould be carefully obſerved and attended to</p>
            <p>But I deſign not to inſiſt upon this any further, than by acquainting you briefly with two things, which clear and confirm the Propoſition.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The extraordinary uſefulneſs of this Truth to us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The extraordinary ſtrangeneſs of the Thing it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The extraordinary uſefulneſs of this Truth to us. What is neither ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in it ſelf, nor uſeful to us, we juſtly overlook, and take no notice of; or if we do, we therein betray our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and imprudence.</p>
            <p>Now we have ordinarily many Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts and Deſigns on foot, but we readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledg, that we are bound on all accounts to purſue with moſt care, earneſtneſs and diligence, thoſe things we are aſſured will moſt of all farther our higheſt Intereſts, thoſe Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments we are moſt affected with, and prefer and value above all the reſt. If a Man have a Trial depending for his whole Eſtate, or for his Life, and can hear of a certain Courſe he may take, which will infallibly ſecure his Cauſe,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43210:17"/>he will attend unto this Buſineſs, before all his other Affairs; and though there be other Matters he would be diligent and induſtrious about, were this his principal Buſineſs well ſetled, yet he omits and neglects them; he lays them aſide at preſent, that he may follow his greater and more important Affair, with greater freedom and leſs diſturbance. Now there is nothing ſo much concerns us, as to be truly and ſavingly acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Riches of Divine Grace, to be ſenſible of the gracious Viſits Chriſt doth make, and to embrace and cloſe with his bleſſed Motions. You may loſe your Lands, be rob'd of your Mony, have your Houſes and Goods all burnt about your Ears, and yet not be undone, nor irreparably miſerable. But if you are ignorant of Chriſt, and regardleſs of his Viſits, and deſtitute of an Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in his Love, you are poor, deluded, miſerable, unhappy Wretches, whatever Portion you have of the Wealth, and Honour, and Applauſe of this World.</p>
            <p>Indeed, too many ſlight Chriſt, and make no account of his Love. People who are ſunk in their Luſts, whoſe Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings Satan hath blinded, in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43210:17"/>whom Satan rules, and by whom they are hurried away headlong towards Hell, as the <hi>Gadarens</hi> Swine were into the Deep. But, O! let us take heed we do not tread in their Steps, leſt we drink of their Cup, and partake of their Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle tells you, <hi>It is a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Saying, and worthy of all acceptation, that Jeſus Chriſt came into the World to ſave Sinners,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.15. What is it then, that after all his Sufferings, and being aſcended into Glory, he doth ſtill continue to expreſs and teſtify as great Love as ever to us? Shall we deſpiſe the choiceſt offers of his Love? Shall we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe, or take no notice of ſuch a Truth as this, that Chriſt doth ſtoop to viſit us, and importunes our acceptance of him? O, what vile, what unworthy, what ungrateful Perſons ſhall we then approve our ſelves! In how forlorn and deplorable a State are all the ſtubborn and obſtinate deſpiſers and contemners of Chriſt! <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3. O, Sirs! did you underſtand the worth of thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Souls you are intruſted with; were you truly ſenſible of the ſad and miſerable Eſtate you are in by Nature,
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:43210:18"/>this Love expreſs'd, but by Piety and Obedience? <hi>If ye love me, keep my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments,</hi> John 14.15. <hi>Ye are my Friends, if ye do whatſoever I command you,</hi> John 15.14. What an incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is it to a Holy Life, when we can truly ſay, we are hereby teſtifying our Love to our dear Saviour, in ſuch a way as he doth moſt approve? Whom ſhould we ſerve, whom ſhould we obey, if not him who hath, and doth love us ſtill in ſo extraordinary a manner?</p>
            <p>We are ('tis true) too prone to ſerve Satan and our Luſts; but what reaſon have we to do ſo? Is Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Hell ſo ſweet and ſo obliging, we ſhould drudg and toil all our time for ſuch a Purchaſe? Can you ſeriouſly think Satan who tempts and ſollicites you to Sin, hath any love for you? And will you ſerve him who ſeeks your eternal ruin ſo induſtriouſly, before the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who hath given you ſo many convincing Teſtimonies of his Love?</p>
            <p>It is an amazing, and very ſad thing to obſerve, how People do prefer the drudgery and vaſſalage of Satan, before the liberty and freedom their Saviour
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43210:18"/>hath purchaſed for them. That not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding Chriſt doth love them ſo affectionately, yet Satan ſhould have ſo many to run violently after him to Hell; and Chriſt ſhould have ſo few to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him to the Manſions of Bliſs and Glory.</p>
            <p>It is a ſad, but yet too juſt a repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of Man's Folly, Ingratitude, and Wickedneſs, which St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> makes, when he brings in the Devil boaſting againſt Chriſt, and inſulting over People in this manner; <hi>Ego pro iſtis nec ſanguinem fudi,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>(Serm. de Ely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos)</hi> I have not ſhed one drop of Blood for any of all theſe my Followers; I never took any pains to do them any good; my ſtudy, and care, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence hath ever been, and ever ſhall be, to bring them to Death and Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and yet notwithſtanding all this, <hi>Tuos tales, demonſtra mihi, Chriſte.</hi> Shew me, O Chriſt, ſo many, ſuch buſy, ſuch painful, and ſuch dutiful Servants of thine any where, as I can ſhew thee eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where of mine. Shall the Envy and Malice of Satan be more powerful with you, to draw you into Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than the prodigious Love of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43210:19"/>the Son of God, to win you unto Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Glory?</p>
            <p>O! were we but duly affected with the Love Chriſt bears to us, we ſhould not be able to reſiſt its Charms! O, what pious exemplary, praiſing Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans would this make us? Who ever hath a true and real ſenſe of this Love in his Heart, will be transformed by it into the likeneſs of him, who doth thus love him. The reaſon why we are no better, that we reſemble Chriſt ſo little, is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are ignorant of his Love; tho we may know ſomewhat of it notional<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo as to tincture and adorn our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, yet our Hearts are not touched with it, and brought under its Efficacy and Power. Were our Hearts but mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the conſideration and ſenſe of this Love, O how powerfully would it engage us in the Ways and Work of our Saviour! With what vigour and delight ſhould we be carried through the whole courſe of Chriſtian Duty, and new Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience?</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is of exceding great uſe, for our ſupport and comfort under Trials, Temptations, Sufferings and Troubles in the World; and when we are exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43210:19"/>with deep apprehenſions of our own ſinfulneſs and vileneſs. Affliction doth try Friends. A Man whilſt he doth proſper and flouriſh in the World, ſhall have many pretended Friends, who will fall from and diſown him in Adverſity. We are ſubject to Trials and Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, under which all thoſe things that flatter our Senſes, and which People court and labour for with all their might, will either take their flight from us, or at beſt, lie by us, as inſipid uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs things: Nothing but a ſenſe of Chriſt's Love will then befriend us.</p>
            <p>And I know not any ſort of People more expoſed to Trials and Aſſaults in the World, than the People of God; nor are there any whom Satan doth or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily ſet upon with fiercer violence, than poor Sinners, when firſt beginning to look out after, and liſten unto Chriſt. And as theſe are liable to ſuch Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſo God provides for their ſupport and comfort under them. If it be a great relief to a Perſon under outward trouble, that he hath a Friend to ſtand by him, and counſel him, and appear for him, what is it to a true Believer to be aſſured of the Love of Chriſt? That he
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43210:20"/>hath one on his ſide, who is alſufficient for him, be his Circumſtances what they will, and who will never fail him nor forſake him?</p>
            <p>What tho I be poor and miſerable, and deſtitute and afflicted in the World? What tho I be made as the filth and the off-ſcouring of all things? Chriſt loves me never the leſs for that. Nay, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe I have great Doubts in my Mind, and my Soul is full of heavineſs for my Sins, and I am ready to cry out, O! my Sins are not ordinary and uſual Sins, they have been aggravated above mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure! I cannot ſee any thing in my ſelf, but impurity, filth, and guilt. I do not perceive how any thing but Damnation can belong to me! O my Miſery! O my Unhappineſs! O my Guilt! I am ſo la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with Sin, my Guilt lies ſo heavy upon my Spirit; Terror and amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, fear and horror, do ſo prevail in my Soul, I am not able to bear up under the ſame, my Heart fails me, and my Spirit is gone! Why now, one glimps of Chriſt, one taſte of his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, a ſenſe of his Love, will revive and exhilerate the Soul, and diſperſe all theſe Clouds, theſe Darkneſſes and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43210:20"/>Storms. There is no condition a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon can be in, but if Chriſt will dart in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him a Ray of his ſpecial Love, he will thence receive mighty, even inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible ſupport and comfort. The continued Love of Chriſt, is the moſt ſovereign Cordial in every Eſtate and Condition. We may go through Fire and Water, we may adventure upon any ſuffering for the Name of Chriſt, being aſſured of his Love. O! what an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent chearing Scripture is that of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> Chap. 8. v. 35, to the end?</p>
            <p>What would the Scripture be to us; how ſhould we be effectually excited and encouraged to a courſe of Piety? Or, what could ſupport us under Burthens and Troubles, if Chriſt did not conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue his Love to Sinners?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2ly,</hi> In the ſecond place we are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the extraordinary ſtrangeneſs of the thing it ſelf. We commonly take as particular notice as we can, of ſtrange and unwonted Occurrences. How do People view and obſerve Comets and Blazing Stars? How do they flock to ſee any ſtrange ſort of Beaſt, when ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited to be ſeen? We admire and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43210:21"/>wonder at things, which are conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble only by reaſon of their ſtrangeneſs and rarity; Things which are not of any great worth, nor cannot produce us any profit and real advantage. O! therefore, let us be ſo wiſe as to turn all our admiration unto that which is truly ſtrange, and equally advantagious and comfortable?</p>
            <p>The Love of Chriſt to Sinners, is the ſtrangeſt thing that ever was: <hi>Without controverſy great is the Myſtery of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: God was manifeſt in the Fleſh, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified in the Spirit, ſeen of Angels, preached unto the Gentiles, believed on in the World, and received up into Glory,</hi> 1 Tim. 3.16. This is a thing ſo ſtrange, even in the firſt Inſtances of it, the bleſſed Angels ſtand amazed at it, and deſire to look into it, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12.</p>
            <p>If a Prince, the only Son of a King or Emperor, ſhould condeſcend to take notice of a mean traiterous Wretch, ready to have all the Torments and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments his Treaſon deſerved, inflicted on him, and plead for this Perſon; yea, deny himſelf all the Pleaſures, Honours, and Satisfactions in his Father's Court; yea, ſubmit himſelf to all manner of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43210:21"/>Indignities for many Years together, to procure the other's Pardon. And being at laſt received to Court again, and living in the greateſt pomp and ſplendour, ſhould come to this Perſon whoſe Life he had ſaved at the forementioned rate, and entreat and beſeech, and court him to be reconciled to him; and that an intimate familiarity and correſpondence may be ſetled betwixt them, promiſing him all the Entertainments and Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions he doth participate of himſelf, Would not this be looked on by all as a moſt prodigious Inſtance of Affection and Love?</p>
            <p>But alas! what is this to that we are now diſcourſing of? Here is the Son of God, who is equal with God, God bleſſed for ever; who is the Brightneſs of his Father's Glory, and the expreſs Image of his Perſon; whoſe Name is Wonderful, Counſellor, The mighty God, The Everlaſting Father, The Prince of Peace. This is the Perſon who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcended to take on him our Nature; who lived for many Years together a Life that was very mean, and to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance very contemptible. What Indignities did he ſuffer from Men!
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43210:22"/>how deep did he drink of the Cup of God's Wrath! when groaning, and praying, and ſweating Blood in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den! when expoſtulating ſo earneſtly with his Father on the Croſs! He ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Death, yea, he became obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to Death, even the <hi>Death of the Croſs:</hi> The moſt painful, the moſt lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering, the moſt ignominious and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſort of Death then known in the World. And all this was to reconcile Sinners and Enemies unto God, and to ſave them from that eternal Miſery and Damnation they could no other way be ſaved from. And after all this, having raiſed himſelf to Life, and being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into Glory, he continues his Love to theſe Sinners, and many ways impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes and ſollicites them to accept of the Mercy and Bleſſings which coſt him ſo dear; and to yield themſelves up into the Bonds of Friendſhip, that a conſtant mutual correſpondence may be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained betwixt them. Is not this an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible aſtoniſhing Prodigy of Love? what can be compared unto it? What Heart ſo hard, ſuch Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſuch Love, ſuch paſſionate court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will not ſoften and overcome? What
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43210:22"/>ſo ſtrange, what ſo obliging as this, that the Son of God ſhould entreat and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech Rebels to accept of Pardon? ſhould court and make ſo much ado, be ſo importunate, and keep ſuch a ſtir with us, who are only held by his Hand from falling into Hell, to accept of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven! There is nothing ſo ſtrange as this, unleſs it be that curſed Heart, which is too obdurate and ſtubborn to be overcome and won, by ſo kind, ſo winning, and ſo mighty a Force as this is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Applic.</hi> What care now ſhould we take to be throughly inſtructed and ſetled in this great Truth? Do not la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour only to be acquainted with it in the Theory, but endeavour and pray that a ſaving Knowledg and Belief of it may be wrought in you by the Spirit of God. This is a Matter concerns thee much, thy Salvation depends upon it. If thou loſe thy Soul, thou loſeſt all: If thou art ignorant of the Love of Chriſt, if this Love have no influence on thee, thou art miſerable indeed. All true Comfort is wrap'd up in this. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12. O ſtudy this great Truth,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43210:23"/>and do not deſiſt or leave off, till it have its proper influence on thy Affections, Heart, and Life. Let the Love of Chriſt conſtrain thee. Reſolve to know nothing but Jeſus Chriſt, and him cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. Admire and adore the Love of Chriſt: Improve the knowledg and conſideration of it, to fix and promote thy Faith, thy Love, thy Hope, thy Patience, and every other Grace.</p>
            <p>But I will not inſiſt any longer on this firſt word, which is introductory, and ſhould lead us attentively unto that which followeth.</p>
            <p>The reſt of the Verſe acquaints us with our bleſſed Saviour's ſeeking for, and endeavouring to get admittance with us: and the Priviledges which ſhall accrue to thoſe who hearken to him, and receive him.</p>
            <p>I ſhall confine my ſelf now unto the firſt of theſe, which is repreſented to us in theſe words, <hi>I ſtand at the Door and knock.</hi> Though in diſcourſing of this, I ſhall have occaſion to acquaint you with the main Importance of ſome of the following words, <hi>viz. If any Man hear my Voice, and open the Door.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:43210:23"/>
            <p>Our Saviour's ſeeking and endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to get admittance with us, is here expreſt by three words.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Standing.</item>
               <item>2. Knocking.</item>
               <item>3. The word <hi>Door.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The Perſon, or rather the Heart of the Perſon, becauſe of its being the principal Part of Man, and the Seat of the Affection, is often compared to, and called a Houſe, a Temple, a Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. God hath a ſecret and real com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with the Soul of every true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever. He communicates much of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and imparts his Heavenly Graces unto every ſuch Perſon; He ſets up his Government in that Soul, and he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth his gracious Concernment with that Soul, by dwelling in it, by making that Perſon his Houſe and Habitation. <hi>Jeſus anſwered and ſaid, If a Man love me, he will keep my Words, and my Father will love him; and we will come unto him, and make our abode with him,</hi> Joh. 14.23. ſee <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.15.</p>
            <p>The Lord Jeſus makes very gracious Propoſals to us; He offers us his Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:43210:24"/>his Graces, his Spirit, the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of his Death and Paſſion, Himſelf. And entreats and beſeeches us to accept of theſe, and give them room in our Hearts. His addreſſing of himſelf to us by way of inſtruction, perſwaſion, and tendering of theſe to us, is called his knocking at the Door. Our learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him, accepting of, and cloſing with his Tenders, is called, our hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Voice, and opening to him.</p>
            <p>It may be proper here to take notice;</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Of our Saviour's Poſture.</item>
               <item>2. Of his Geſture.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. His Poſture. <hi>Behold, I ſtand.</hi> Which notes both his Patience; how long he doth wait to be gracious, and what danger we are in, if we do not make a good uſe and improvement of his Patience and long-ſuffering, for he is in ſuch a Poſture, as notes a readineſs of departure if he be not admitted.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His Geſture. <hi>And knock.</hi> Which notes his earneſtneſs and importunity. The Lord Jeſus, when he makes his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits unto the Soul, is not willing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43210:24"/>without beſtowing ſome Bleſſing. He ſeems reſolved not to take a denial. He will faſten ſome Good, ſome Bleſſing on thee, if there be any thing, either of ingenuity or of modeſty in thee.</p>
            <p>The Phraſe is taken, from what is ordinarily obſerved in the Viſits which People make to one another. As the Perſon which goeth to ſee another, doth commonly ſtand before the Door of that Houſe where the other's Abode is; and deſiring to have entrance, knocks, and makes a noiſe at the Door, till, if any one be in the Houſe, he be taken notice of; which argues, he hath a deſire to have ſome diſcourſe and converſe with the Perſon he comes to viſit. Thus Chriſt ſets forth his deſire, and his ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs, to have ſome commerce and familiarity with poor Sinners. He waits, he knocks, he uſeth all kind of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity with them.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine I deſign to inſiſt on a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle from theſe words, is this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord Jeſus Chriſt doth wait long, and uſeth much importunity with
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43210:25"/>Sinners, to prevail with them to accept of him and his Benefits. He ſtands at the door long, and knocks often, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we will take notice of him, and open unto him. Indeed, his own Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and Servants, are too apt to forget him, and to ſuffer him to wait and ſtay long, when he makes his after Addreſſes to them, before they riſe and let him in. We are too prone to turn a deaf Ear to him, and admit any thing as an excuſe for our not giving him ſo ſpeedy and grateful a reception as we owe him. How often do even Believers forget themſelves, and grow ſo remiſs and drowſy, as to provoke him to withdraw himſelf, and deny them the ſence of his gracious Preſence and Love! So that they muſt ſeek long, and undergo much trouble, before he will be found of them again. This you may ſee fully proved, if you ſeriouſly read and weigh the fifth Chapter of the <hi>Song of Solomon,</hi> from v. <hi>1ſt,</hi> to the <hi>9th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if thoſe who have in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure underſtood their need of Chriſt, and been affected with his Excellencies, and taſted how good the Lord is, may grow ſo negligent and careleſs, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43210:25"/>be very much wondered at, if Chriſt, when he makes his Addreſſes to others, who are ſtill in their natural Eſtate, be not preſently hearkened unto, but muſt uſe importunity before he find admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. But yet the Sinner's either refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or neglecting to hear him, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with him, is a thing ſo ill, nothing can excuſe it.</p>
            <p>Now this ſhews the weakneſs of Grace in many who are already regenerated. And what need the Beſt have to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways on their watch. And likewiſe, how ſtrangely ſtupid and ſtubborn Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are, till by the operation of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, their Hearts are effectually wrought on and awakened. And, O how wonderful is the Condeſcention of the Bleſſed Jeſus, in that he takes ſo much notice of, and doth with ſuch pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and earneſtneſs court, and ſtrive to overcome ſuch vile, ſuch ſenſleſs, and ſuch unworthy Creatures!</p>
            <p>It is Chriſt that firſt takes notice of us, not we of him. <hi>We love him, becauſe he loved us firſt,</hi> 1 John 4.19. If Chriſt did never love and importune us, we ſhould never love him. Should not Chriſt come and knock at our Doors,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:43210:26"/>we ſhould never think of, nor look after him in good earneſt.</p>
            <p>How ſhould we ſtand amazed at this! It was when we were Enemies that Chriſt died for us; and it is whilſt we are in a ſtate of Enmity, that he comes and entreats us to be reconciled to him. God might eaſily and fully have glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied his Juſtice in our eternal Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and yet how earneſt is he with us, to accept of the happy Fruits of his Kindneſs? It is, whilſt we lie wallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in our Blood, without pitty, that he ſets his Love upon us, and ſaith unto us, <hi>Live.</hi> It is Chriſt's Work to bring us to a compliance with himſelf. He loves us firſt, he manifeſts his Love firſt, and he makes thoſe diſcoveries of his Love powerful, &amp; of force to work upon our ſtubborn Natures, and hard Hearts, before we will yield and acknowledg, either our own emptineſs and need of him, or his wonderful Love and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcention towards us. It is Chriſt that ſaith, <hi>I will have Mercy upon her that had not obtained Mercy, and I will ſay to them which were not my People, Thou art my People; and then they ſhall ſay, Thou art my God,</hi> Hoſ. 2.23. You ſee Chriſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43210:26"/>ſpeaks firſt, before we acknowledg him. Lord, what is Man that thou art mindful of him! or the Son of Man, that thou haſt ſuch regard unto him! What a Miracle of Condeſcention and Love is this, that the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that the Great and Eternal God ſhould thus court and ſollicit Duſt and Aſhes! ſhould repreſent himſelf ſo in love with ſinful Worms!</p>
            <p>In diſcourſing of this Truth, I ſhall endeavour,</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. To explain and illuſtrate this, of Chriſt's waiting to be gracious to Sinners, and importuning them to accept of him.</item>
               <item>II. To ſhew you what our receiving of Chriſt doth import.</item>
               <item>III. To enquire what are the main Inſtances which hinder us from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of Chriſt into our Hearts.</item>
               <item>IV. To offer a Reaſon or two, why Chriſt is thus importunate with Sinners.</item>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:43210:27"/>
               <item>V. To make ſome Application of the whole.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">I. I ſhall ſay ſomething concerning Chriſt's waiting to be gracious to Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and importuning them for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance into their Hearts. Theſe two things are both implied in, and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by theſe words, <hi>I ſtand at the Door, and knock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The one argues his Patience, and the ſtay he makes to be gracious unto us. This is the word, <hi>Stand, I ſtand at the Door.</hi> Now, how long hath Chriſt ſtood at your Doors? how long and often hath he been calling unto you for admittance, and as yet to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe? Indeed, ſome receive him very early: Happy they who bid ſo worthy, ſo deſirable, ſo good a Gueſt, welcome betimes! They who are from their ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Years acquainted with Chriſt, with whom they conſtantly keep a corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence, and who hath long reigned in their Hearts, are happy People in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. Theſe are truly Heaven's Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:43210:27"/>
            <p>But I am afraid the number of ſuch is not very great. Alas! Chriſt is a great while ſlighted and contemned, before he is in any tolerable meaſures taken tice of, and hearkned unto in the World. O the Patience that Jeſus Chriſt doth exerciſe towards Sinners! How many Days, and Weeks, yea Months, and Years, doth he ſtand waiting, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we will hear his Voice, and open unto him?</p>
            <p>It is our great fault, and unhappineſs too, that after we are in ſome meaſure acquainted with Chriſt, we are prone to neglect our Watch, and ſuffer our love to him to abate, and almoſt die: So that when he makes his freſh Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches to us, and calls for admittance into our Hearts, we are ready to make excuſes, till we force him to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw and hide himſelf from us, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.2, 3.</p>
            <p>But alas! how many Years together do many ſtand out and reſiſt him, tho he uſe never ſo many methods to win, and bring them to a compliance.</p>
            <p>Nay, Chriſt doth not only wait all this time, but he manifeſts extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry patience on the account of their
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43210:28"/>demeanour towards him. Were there any one who had done us an injury, and we ſhould go to, and promiſe him we will paſs by the wrong, and entreat him that we may be Friends; and that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhould refuſe to let us into his Houſe, ſhould ſet us at defiance, and revile and reproach us, and do us greater Injuries than before, how would our Blood boil? how would our Paſſions flame? how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconcileable ſhould we be to him for the future? But Jeſus Chriſt doth other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to us; He comes to us when in a ſtate of Rebellion againſt him. He is ready to pardon us, pleads with us to accept his Favours, and demonſtrates how real and hearty he is. He does, as it were, lay before us his Sufferings, and tell us, that all theſe Calamities, Preſſures, and Sorrows were undergone for our ſakes: And tho all this prove unſuccesful, we ſtill refuſe to hearken to him, and do proudly and contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly turn away from him, he doth not deſiſt, but ſtill ſtands and waits to ſee whether we will come to our ſelves, whether we will become more calm, and wiſe, and at laſt accept of the gracious Offers he doth make us.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:43210:28"/>
            <p>O! what a number of Affronts and Provocations doth the Lord Jeſus Chriſt patiently bear and paſs by, whilſt waiting to be gracious to his Enemies! How do Sinners ſet him at nought, and offer him the greateſt contempt they can! and ſtill he bears all, and ſtands waiting at their Doors.</p>
            <p>Sinner! Thou that liveſt in known Sins, under the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, and a profeſſion of the Faith of Chriſt; thou haſt had Chriſt waiting on thee a long while. Thou haſt, as it were, heard him tell thee, It was Sin, even thy Sins, that made him a Man of Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, and occaſioned his being reckoned amongſt Tranſgreſſors; that thy Sins contracted on him that load and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, which made him ſweat drops of Blood under the weight of it: That thy Sins nailed him to the Croſs: That thy Drunkenneſs, thy Intemperance, thy Wantonneſs, thy Prophaneneſs, thy Swearing, thy Worldly-mindedneſs, thy Sabbath-breaking, and thy other Sins, made him, when on the Croſs, cry out, with ſo much apprehenſion and earneſtneſs, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> And doth Chriſt after
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:43210:29"/>all this wait on thee, and importune thee to receive him; and wilt thou dare, after all, to reject him? Thou canſt not (however) but acknowledg, that if after all this he continues thee the tenders of his Love, that his Patience is wonderful, thou muſt needs own, that to refuſe him admittance, and deſpiſe his Offers, is very diſingenuous.</p>
            <p>O! what ſtubbornneſs do many teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy towards Chriſt, after he hath been long treating with them in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner? Has not Chriſt told thee theſe things in his Word? Has he not (as it were) come to thee, and ſaid, Behold, Sinner, theſe Hands, and theſe Feet, which were nailed to the Croſs on thy account, to teſtify my Love to thee? See how I was forſaken by all! what I ſuffered for thy Sins! how I was trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted! in what manner my extraordinary Grief did vent it ſelf! And now, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, I come to thee, deſiring to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of thee, and entreating thee to accept the Benefits I have purchaſed by all my grievous Sufferings! And wilt thou ſtill reject him? Wilt thou chide and rate thy Saviour away, after ſo many teſtimonies of incomprehenſible
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:43210:29"/>Kindneſs, Patience, and Love? Wilt thou, by thy carriage towards him, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that thou approveſt what the Jews did unto him? Wilt thou, by a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued repeating of thy old Wickedneſs, diſcover how deſirous thou art to cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cify him again, and what pleaſure thou takeſt in trampling his precious Blood under thy Feet? O, how great then is thy Guilt! how is thy Wickedneſs ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated? What mayſt thou well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect will become of thee? How dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful is thy State! how great is thy Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger! But now, if after all this, Chriſt doth ſtill wait, and make thee new ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Mercy; how aſtoniſhing muſt thou needs acknowledg his Love and his Patience to be?</p>
            <p>The Patience of Chriſt doth moſt ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally appear, in bringing home at laſt thoſe Sinners who have been very noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and who have laboured againſt him, and ſtood out againſt, and reſiſted him a great while.</p>
            <p>O! let this prevail with you all to yield up your ſelves ſpeedily to Chriſt. You have reſiſted him too long already; take heed of repeating your Affronts againſt him, ſeeing he hath born with
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:43210:30"/>you ſo patiently hitherto. Surely he hath waited long enough, O, delay him no longer. The Fruit and Effect may be dreadful, if you reſiſt any farther; the Lord will not always be trifled with. Though the Offers of Grace may be long continued, they will not laſt for ever, if you go on ſtubbornly to deſpiſe and reject them. Take heed of refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to receive and entertain Chriſt, once more, when he comes unto thee, leſt thou ſhouldſt provoke him to depart from thee, with reſolution never to make thee a gracious viſit, or ſee thee with favour any more. Do not thou provoke him to ſwear in his Wrath, thou ſhalt never enter into his Reſt. Canſt thou endure the eternal Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Almighty God? Canſt thou bear up under the direful and aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Puniſhments, which contemned Grace, and abuſed Patience and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs expoſe to? Canſt thou dwell with everlaſting Burnings? O, let the Long-ſuffering, the Patience, and the Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thy Saviour, lead thee to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and prevail with thee to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of, and cloſe with him and his gracious Offers.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:43210:30"/>
            <p>This ſhall ſerve at this time, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt's waiting to be gracious unto Sinners. I proceed to ſay ſomething,</p>
            <p n="2">II. In the ſecond place, of his impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuning Sinners for admittance. This is noted by the word <hi>knock.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt doth not only wait long, but uſeth much importunity, and is very earneſt to get admittance with Sinners. He knocks, and knocks again; he repeats his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties, and often renews his earneſt Sollicitations, that we will not reject and deſpiſe him, but admit him into our Hearts, and bid him welcome. Now, what Condeſcention is this, that the Son of God ſhould court and perſwade us with ſo much warmth and fervour? That he who cannot receive any advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage from us, ſhould thus importune us for our own advantage!</p>
            <p>Indeed, this doth plainly manifeſt our baſeneſs and ſtupidity, in that we are ſo hard to be wrought on, and affected with our moſt important Intereſts. And it doth as certainly and fully diſplay and upbraid our wilfulneſs and impiety, when we ſtand out and finally reſiſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:43210:31"/>Chriſt, as it doth demonſtrate the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parallel'd condeſcention and kindneſs of our Saviour.</p>
            <p>O! what Demonſtrations have we of the tenderneſs of Chriſt to Sinners? How do his Bowels yearn over us, when we are inconſiderately ruining our ſelves? How often doth he knock and entreat us to yield to him, and accept of him and his Benefits? O, how hard and ſtubborn are our Hearts! what, will not all the Divine Methods and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices win us, and bring us into a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with him, that loveth us above Life and Death?</p>
            <p>I need mention but two Generals to evidence more diſtinctly unto you, how earneſt and importunate the Lord Jeſus is to be received by us.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Arguments he doth uſe to perſwade us to accept of him.</item>
               <item>2. The Inſtruments he doth imply a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this Work, <hi>viz.</hi> to win us to comply with his gracious Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and offers.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. The Arguments he doth uſe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with us to accept of Him. He
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:43210:31"/>urgeth the ſtrongeſt Arguments, and preſſeth on us thoſe Conſiderations, which carry along with them the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt force and weight imaginable. And theſe are managed with all the heartineſs and affectionateneſs that is poſſible. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments many, ſtrong, various, and ſuch as are moſt proper to have an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence on our Affections, Judgments; and Minds. Were any Motions urged, that had but the thouſandth part of the reaſon, the leaſt of theſe hath, to engage us to ſtrike in, and cloſe with any thing for our ſecular Advantage, how effectual would they prove! No Difficulties, no Straights, no Diſcouragements would affright or diſhearten us. But when the greateſt and moſt weighing Inſtances, as the Divine Wiſdom can pitch upon, are urged by the Lord himſelf to engage us not to forſake our own Mercies, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to and cloſe with our only Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Alas! how unapprehenſive, how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concerned are we? We are then as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle moved, as if the Arguments had no weight in them, or we had no Souls to take care of, and be ſaved.</p>
            <p>If Satan hath a mind to draw us unto any Sin, or engage us in ſome deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:43210:32"/>and damning courſe, how eaſily doth he prevail? how ſoon doth he gain our Ear, our Hand, our Heart? How ſuddenly doth he hurry us into what he pleaſeth? Yea, Men like our ſelves can eaſily work upon our Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and prevail with us to do thoſe things which will haſten our Miſery, our Shame, our Deſtruction. But, alas! Chriſt may ſtand, and call, and warn, and entreat us by ever ſo many Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, and yet have no admittance amongſt us. We deal with our Saviour, as the wanton and undutiful Child doth, when he lets an Enemy into the Houſe at the firſt word. But when his Parent calls and knocks, he ſits unconcerned, turns a deaf Ear, and never takes any notice, though that Relation knock ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo loud, and be very importunate to be let in. We are ready to follow Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, and do what he would have us to do, if he do but promiſe us a little Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or Wealth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But Chriſt is ſhut out, and not hearkned unto, though he is moſt importunate, and doth urge the weightieſt Arguments to prevail with us to attend unto him.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:43210:32"/>
            <p>The Arguments he doth urge are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry many: It ſhall ſuffice at preſent to name a few of them, with a brief inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of their worth and excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He lays before us his own tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent Excellencies and Perfections. The Dignity of his Perſon, and how wonderful his Condeſcention is, in that he is pleaſed to make ſuch Vouchſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments unto us. <hi>He is the Brightneſs of the Father's Glory, and the expreſs Image of his Perſon; and he upholdeth all things by the Word of his Power,</hi> Heb. 1.3. He is God over all, bleſſed for ever-more, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.5. And what! ſhall the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal God be repulſed, when he makes ſuch importunate Addreſſes to moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Worms? Shall we deny admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to <hi>the high and lofty One who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiteth Eternity; whoſe Name is Holy, and dwelleth in the high and holy Place;</hi> when he condeſcendeth to come to us, and earneſtly entreateth us, to let him have his abode with us? He is not a mean contemptible Perſon which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Love to us, whoſe Favour we may loſe and be never the worſe, whoſe Kindneſs and Love, if withdrawn, may
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:43210:33"/>be made up another way, or by another Perſon. He is God, He is the Lord of Glory: The Angels adore and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, glorify and worſhip him. He can and will make thee truly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakably bleſſed and happy, if thou hearken to his Voice and entertain him. Thou muſt needs be unconceivably miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable without him; he has Power to make thee happy or miſerable. If thou receive him, he will conduct thee to Heaven, and conſtitute thee perfect and unalterably bleſſed. But if thou ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornly and finally deſpiſeſt him, and trampleſt under thy Feet the offers of his Love and Grace, he is able to puniſh thee for thy contempt, and he will caſt thee into, and burn thee in Hell to all Eternity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He repreſents unto us the miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and undone condition we are natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in. That whilſt without him, we are Aliens from the Common-wealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> we do not belong to the Society of thoſe the Lord hath choſen and ſet apart for himſelf; we are Strangers from the Covenant of Promiſe, we have nothing to do with thoſe great and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Priviledges which are made over
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:43210:33"/>to them who are intereſted in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſpecial Love. We have no hope, we are in a deſperate condition as to hereafter, without any true and ſolid ground to encourage our ſelves to hope it ſhall be well with us. We are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God in the World, we are deſtitute of true and ſound Notions of God, and without an intereſt in him as our recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.12. Now, what have ſuch Perſons to be proud of? we <hi>who are dead in Treſpaſſes and Sins,</hi> Epheſ. 2.1. What have we to be conceited of, that we ſhould refuſe to accept of Chriſt's Offers, that we ſhould think ſcorn to entertain him? The diſcovery of our natural Eſtate, ſhould make us haſten to the Lord Jeſus with all the ſpeed we can. But alas, it is our not being ſenſible of our Condition, our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity, our not believing that we are ſo worthleſs, unclean, and miſerable, as indeed we are, that makes us ſlight Chriſt, and refuſe his gracious Offers.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He makes known how real and extraordinary his Love is to us. He does not complement us with words, but hath a Heart for us. O, what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of Love hath he given us?
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:43210:34"/>He hath done as much to approve the ſincerity of his Love to us, as can be deſired or imagined. Sinner, there is no ground for thee to queſtion the truth of his Love. He hath vindicated and cleared his ſincerity beyond all poſſibility of ſuſpicion and doubt. He pleads with the Sinner, proteſts his Love to him, and argues the matter with him. Behold, I have loved thee ſo long al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready with a tranſcendent Love; And what is it thou wouldſt or canſt deſire, to make it appear my Love is hearty and real? Do'ſt thou expect I ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove my Love, by ſuffering ſome great hardſhips for thy ſake? Behold, I have done that, and more, I have been ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and contemned, I have been abuſed and laugh'd at; I have been derided, and mock'd, and ſpit upon; nay, I have ſweat Blood for thee, I have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone inexpreſſible Agonies in my Mind, ſuch troubles and griefs in my Soul, as no Tongue can explain, for thy ſake. I have endured the frowns, and born the diſpleaſure of an angry God, and incenſed Father, to preſerve and ſave thee. Here behold with thine own Eyes the Marks in my Hands, and in my
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:43210:34"/>Feet, thoſe Nails have made which faſtned me to the Croſs! ſee the Scars on my Forehead, which were torn there by that Crown which was violently and reproachfully thruſt on my Head! Nay, I did lay down my Life for thee! I waxed not weary in compaſſing thy Salvation, though the Pains and Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings I endured were very many, very grievous and afflicting. Death it ſelf hath not quench'd nor conquered the Love I did bear unto thee. Now, who can reſiſt the Arguings of a Saviour! Do's Chriſt plead his Love and his Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings with thee? do's he conjure thee, by them, to accept of him? and wilt thou ſtill ſtand out and reject him? O, how ſtubborn, how invincible an Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del, how vile and unpitiable a Wretch wilt thou prove thy ſelf to be, if thou wilt not be moved by the entreaties and courtings of a bleeding Saviour!</p>
            <p n="4">4. He doth urge his Authority over us, and the right he hath unto us. I do not mean only that which doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crue to him by Creation, or from our own particular promiſe and reſignation of our ſelves unto him: But that right he hath to us by purchaſe. We are not our
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:43210:35"/>own to diſpoſe of; The Lord Jeſus hath bought us out of the hands of our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and is become on that account our rightful Lord and Maſter. And how can we refuſe him when he comes unto us, but we muſt contract on our ſelves the dreadful guilt of the moſt deteſtable Rebellion? rebellion againſt Heaven, againſt the Lord of Love, of Mercy, of Life! Our Hearts, our Souls, our Bodies, our whole Man, are purchaſed by him. He has redeemed us unto himſelf, he hath paid a ſufficient price for us, and ſhall we ſhut the Doors againſt him, when he comes to dwell in his own Houſe, the Habitation he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath purchaſed? Should a Servant keep any of us out of a Houſe we have dearly bought, with what indignation ſhould we reſent ſuch uſage? And what may we expect from Chriſt, if we will detain his own purchaſe from him, and not admit him to have an abode with us? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19, 20. <hi>Luke</hi> 19.27.</p>
            <p>It was a great Sin in the Jews, that they ſlighted and diſowned Chriſt when he came amongſt them. And their Sin was very much aggrevated on this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, that they rejected him, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:43210:35"/>he had a peculiar and ſpecial right unto them, <hi>John</hi> 1.11. O, what will our Sin appear to be, if after that Chriſt hath bought us with his moſt precious Blood, we will not accept of, and receive him when he knocks and pleads with us?</p>
            <p n="5">5. He acquaints us with the neceſſity of our admitting him into our Hearts, in order to our own happineſs. What, ſhall we ſin againſt our Lives and our Bleſſedneſs! Shall we caſt away our Souls, and all that is juſtly dear to us, and have nothing to ſay for our ſelves in our own vindication and excuſe? Is there any thing of prudence or of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in doing thus? Doth not our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, doth not that Principle which dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences us from Brutes, deteſt ſuch a thing? Why, if we would not be ſuch Prodigals, it highly concerns us to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of Chriſt. He comes to us, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treats us to accept of him for our own benefit. He cannot receive any advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage or profit by it; he doth not need us: It is for our good he comes to us; he importunes us thus, becauſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out accepting of him, we muſt be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ruined. We are in the way to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:43210:36"/>Hell, Satan and Luſt are hurrying us apace to everlaſting Miſery, and we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be delivered and ſaved any other way than by accepting of him, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12.</p>
            <p n="6">6. He ſets before us the Glory and Inheritance he hath provided for us, and will certainly beſtow on us if we do receive him. The Things Chriſt hath treaſured up for Believers, are not the little tranſitory Things of this World. Theſe Things he caſts abroad with a ſeemingly indifferent hand; he never deſigned to make up a Portion for his own People of theſe periſhing Things. He hath greater and better Things to reward us with; even <hi>an Inheritance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible, undefiled, and which fadeth not away, but is reſerved for us in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.4. He hath taken poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of glorious Manſions, and will come again and receive us unto himſelf, to be for ever where he is, <hi>John</hi> 14.2, 3.</p>
            <p>We have no ground to queſtion our Saviour's Faithfulneſs or Bounty. It is alledged as a ſtrong and convincing Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, that God will not deny any uſeful thing unto his People, becauſe he
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:43210:36"/>hath given up his Son for them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. And can we imagine, that he who hath ſuffered for us, and triumphed over all our Enemies, and hath made ſuch glorious Promiſes as are recorded in his Word, and doth ſtill teſtify ſuch ſtrong Affection and Love towards us, will, if we accept of him, refuſe to confer on us the great and the glorious Things he hath purchaſed for us by his bloody Sufferings? Our Bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, when he was on Earth, prayed that his Servants might be with him where he ſhould be, <hi>John</hi> 17.24. And he ſtill intercedes now he is in Heaven for ſuch, that they may be with him, and will certainly conduct them to, and poſſeſs them for ever of that Glory and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs which infinitely exceeds all Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, and which is fully underſtood by no Creatures but thoſe who do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy it. A Happineſs which is abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly free from all evil, and unpleaſant Mixture, and which is every way com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, and full of every thing that is grateful, pleaſant, and can adminiſter any ſatisfaction: A Happineſs that is ſtable, ſure, and certain, which ſhall laſt to all Eternity, and never ceaſe,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:43210:37"/>decay, nor cloy, but always entertain with raptures of Joy, raviſhing Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and Satisfactions, which ariſe to uninterrupted and conſtant Extaſies.</p>
            <p>Theſe are ſome of the Arguments which are ſtrongly urged to prevail with Sinners to accept of Chriſt. But his Importunity will yet further appear, if we conſider the Inſtruments he doth imploy and make uſe of about this Work. The Inſtruments are many, which are employ'd to entreat and perſwade, and move Sinners to cloſe with the gracious Tenders made them by the Son of God.</p>
            <p>I will name but four.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Holy Spirit is appointed to be Chriſt's Advocate, and is employ'd to plead Chriſt's Cauſe with Sinners. This Holy Spirit hath not only in a miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous way convinc'd the World of Sin, of Righteouſneſs, and of Judgment; but he doth plead often with particular Perſons. Sometimes he works pious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations and deſires in the Soul; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he affects with a penetrating ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of the wretchedneſs of a natural Eſtate. Sometimes he convinces powerfully of a neceſſity of looking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:43210:37"/>Chriſt; ſometimes he moves and perſwades the Soul to cloſe with Chriſt, and accept him upon his own terms. The Spirit of God works variouſly, ſecretly, and powerfully on the Heart; and doth often teſtify of Chriſt, even to thoſe who do a long time, nay, it may be, finally ſtand out and refuſe to cloſe heartily with him.</p>
            <p>But it is a great aggravation of a Perſon's Sin to grieve the Spirit of God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.30. and to quench the Spirit, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.19. To take no notice of Chriſt, but ſtubbornly oppoſe and reſiſt him, when he comes to us, and pleads with us, and entreats us by his Spirit to accept of him.</p>
            <p>O, to what a height doth our Guilt aſcend, when Chriſt ſends his Spirit to treat with us, and we deſpiſe, or take no notice of the workings and witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of this Holy Spirit! What a heightned Crime and Wickedneſs is this, to contemn and make light of Chriſt, after that the Holy Spirit hath been treating with us, and explaining to us, the Dignity of Chriſt, his unvaluable tranſcendent Excellencies, and the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of a Saviour!</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:43210:38"/>
            <p>This is certainly a very great proof and demonſtration of our Saviour's ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs to be admitted by us; that he pleads with us by ſuch an one, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploys his Holy Spirit to tranſact and manage this Buſineſs with us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He ſends his Miniſters on this Errand. The Miniſters of the Goſpel are appointed to be the Preachers of Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation unto the World. They are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted by the Lord Jeſus to plead with Sinners, and endeavour to prevail with them to receive Chriſt, and yield up themſelves to him. And therefore, as you hear, or refuſe to hear them, ſo Chriſt interprets your readineſs or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſs to receive him, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.16.</p>
            <p>The great Work and Buſineſs of the Miniſtry is, to beſeech you, in the Name of Chriſt, to lay down your Enmity, which you have unjuſtly conceived a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and hearken unto his wholſom ſaving Advice and Counſel, even to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of him, that he may dwell with you, and you with him. <hi>Now then we are Ambaſſadors for Chriſt, as though God did beſeech you by us; we pray you in Chriſt's ſtead, be ye reconciled unto God,</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:43210:38"/>2 Cor. 5.20. Now, how often, and with how much earneſtneſs have you been entreated this way, to embrace Chriſt and his Gracious Offers! Were not Chriſt very importunate for admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, what need would there be, that a particular ſort of People ſhould be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed and ſet apart for this very Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to invite, and perſwade, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat People to accept of Chriſt, and his Benefits? <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Jeſus Chriſt doth importune you by his Word. When you read or hear the Holy Scriptures, what urgings and entreatings have you there from Chriſt to accept of him! It is Peoples great Sin, that they ſlight the Scriptures, as they do Miniſters and Ordinances, and are not willing to obſerve Chriſt ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in them. But, O what a zeal and earneſtneſs doth Chriſt manifeſt there, in beſeeching and calling Sinners to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace and accept of him?</p>
            <p>Conſider and weigh theſe few Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, amongſt the many you may meet with, in reading the Word of God; which plainly ſhew how much Chriſt is
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:43210:39"/>concerned for your cloſing with his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Tenders.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His free and ſolemn Invitations. What frank and liberal Promiſes doth he make to all who will but comply with his Call! <hi>Come unto me all ye that are weary and heavy laden, and I will give you reſt,</hi> Matth. 11.28. <hi>Ho, every one that thirſteth, come ye to the Waters; and he that hath no Mony, come ye, buy and eat, yea, come, buy Wine and Milk with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Mony and without Price. Wherefore do ye ſpend Mony for that which is not Bread? and your Labour for that which ſatisfieth not? Hearken diligently unto me, and eat ye that which is good, and let your Soul delight it ſelf in Fatneſs. Incline your Ear, and come unto me: hear, and your Soul ſhall live, and I will make an everlaſting Covenant with you, even the ſure Mercies of</hi> David. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1, 2, 3. You ſee here, that he excepts none, and that he aſſures of the beſt, the moſt uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, the choiceſt, and moſt valuable Bleſſings.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His vehement and affectionate Proteſtations. He ſwears by Himſelf,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:43210:39"/>that his Love is cordial and ſincere. He importunes us often, and condeſcends to argue and expoſtulate with us. <hi>As I live, ſaith the Lord God, I have no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the death of the Wicked, but that the Wicked turn from his way and live; turn ye, turn ye from your evil ways, for why will ye die, O houſe of</hi> Iſrael? <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.11. <hi>Caſt away from you all your Tranſgreſſions whereby ye have tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and make you a new Heart, and a new Spirit: for why will ye die, O Houſe of</hi> Iſrael? <hi>For I have no pleaſure in the death of him that dieth, ſaith the Lord God: wherefore turn your ſelves and live ye.</hi> Ezek. 18.31, 32.</p>
            <p n="3">3. His paſſionate Lamentation over thoſe who do ſtubbornly reject him, and will not accept of him, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he pleads with them thus earneſtly. He wept over them of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> after he had long importuned them in vain. How does he expreſs, by groans and ſighs, his mournful ſorrowful Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, on the account of the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they were wilfully drawing on them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? <hi>O Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem, thou that killeſt the Prophets, and ſtoneſt them
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:43210:40"/>which are ſent unto thee; how often would I have gathered thy Children together, even as a Hen gathereth her Chickens under her Wings, and ye would not?</hi> Matth. 23.37.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Chriſt doth importune us for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance by every Mercy and Judgment. How often are we brought to ſome ſenſe of our need of Chriſt, and to ſome kind of reſolutions to yield and open to him, by the ſtraights, and exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies, and ſufferings we are involved in? though it is our very great Fault, that we are apt to forget all, as ſoon as our pain is over: But what is the true end of every Affliction, but to make us ſee more of the Excellencies of Chriſt, and to endear him unto our Souls? O happy Sufferings! might they all have ſuch an influence on us!</p>
            <p>And what is the end of all God's Mercies, but to lead us to Repentance, and bring us to Chriſt? Why are you thus long preſerved out of Hell? Why are you not at this time tormented and frying in eternal Burnings? Is any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be aſſigned why you ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the Goſpel, yea, the common Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:43210:40"/>of your Lives, but only this, that Chriſt is ſtill waiting to be gracious to you, and that by theſe means he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viting and importuning you to accept of him, and fly from that Damnation which doth not ſlumber, but is haſtning apace upon the whole World of ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sinners? God could as eaſily have diſmiſſed you to the Regions of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Places of moſt dreadful and inſupportable Horror, many Years a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, as any others who are now in Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. All the Mercies, and all the time you have had in the World, were the Fruits of Chriſt's Love, Teſtimonies of his Patience, and Inſtances of his pleading with you to accept of him, and not ruin and undo your ſelves.</p>
            <p>How ſmall a thing would it be, for Chriſt to ſend thee to Hell? to ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, Go thou curſed? Alas, one frown from him would immediately ſink thee into the Earth, into the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſs Pit! And what is it that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves thee, but the tenderneſs of thy Saviour? And for what end doth he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs ſo much regard unto thee, but to try whether his Patience and Lenity, and his allowing thee ſo much time, ſtrength,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:43210:41"/>and ſo many Mercies, will prevail with thee to prize and receive thy Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our!</p>
            <p n="2">II. I am now in the ſecond place to ſhew you, what our receiving Chriſt into our Hearts doth import.</p>
            <p>But before I ſpeak poſitively to this, I will take notice of two or three things, with which People do too commonly falſly pleaſe, and ſatisfy, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently deceive themſelves. We ſhould obſerve theſe, as Mariners do the Rocks and Shelves where others have ſuffered Shipwrack before them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This receiving Chriſt, doth not conſiſt in a bare notional knowledg of him. A Man may, by common inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and ordinary diligence and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, acquire from the Holy Scriptures ſuch Notions concerning Chriſt, as Men do uſually obtain by ſtudy and diligence in any Point of Philoſophy. But this is only ſuch a knowledg as doth float in the Head, and may be in that Perſon who hath not any love and affection to Chriſt: Such may have a knowledg of Chriſt, ſo as to give a plain account of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:43210:41"/>the common ſenſe, or ancient uſe of the Words, wherein the Doctrines con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chriſt are communicated and conveighed unto People. They may give an account of the Grammatical meaning and ſenſe of the words, as well as any others; and yet theſe Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may not entertain Chriſt. They may not underſtand, nor cannot dive into the Spiritual meaning of thoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Julian</hi> knew a great deal concerning Chriſt, and ſo did <hi>Colſus,</hi> but they were great Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <q>The only Principle which enableth a Man for the right judging and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning of Heavenly Things, is the Grace of God's Spirit, which the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Man wanteth; and hence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that as a Man cannot live without a Soul, nor ſee without an Eye, nor hear without an Ear, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe theſe are the Grounds and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples from which Life, and Sight, and Hearing do flow: So no Man can know and ſerve God aright, without God's Spirit enlightning and ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling him by his Grace, becauſe this is the Principle from which all both
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:43210:42"/>ſpiritual Actions and Abilities do ſpring.</q> Maſon <hi>of Hearing and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> p. 328.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It doth not conſiſt in an outward profeſſing to own the Faith of Chriſt. Alas! how many make a general Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Chriſtianity, and of embracing the particular Doctrines of the Goſpel, who take no care to depart from Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty! The very Devils have made as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable a Profeſſion of Chriſt's being the Son of God, as any meer words we can deviſe will amount unto, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.41.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It doth not conſiſt in a bare per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of ſome Duties, in the Name of Chriſt. Performing Duties in the Name of Chriſt, and ſpeaking honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably and much of Chriſt, are very good and commendable, when they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from a right Principle, and ſpring from a real and very ardent Affection to Chriſt. But we muſt take heed leſt we content our ſelves with theſe things, whilſt they may have a falſe Original, or are uſed to improper Ends. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, we muſt be ſure we do not ſtay here, without proceeding further. Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have uſed the Name of Chriſt to
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:43210:42"/>very ill purpoſes, <hi>Acts</hi> 19.13. Many pretend to perform Duties with ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs, in his Name, for whom he hath no reſpect, and who did never truly bid him welcome into their Hearts, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.22, 23.</p>
            <p>Indeed, where Chriſt is received a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, there will be all theſe things in ſome degree and meaſure, but theſe will not be all which will be there. There muſt be ſome knowledg of Chriſt, tho not that which doth only ſoar aloft in the Head, and evaporate, and manifeſt it ſelf only at the Mouth; but ſuch as will influence the Heart and Life. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who receive Chriſt aright, may not be able to expreſs and diſcover their knowledg to others in ſuch appoſite, free, and voluble Expreſſions, as ſome others can, who have nothing of the true Spiritual ſenſe of Divine Truths, or the ſaving Knowledg of Chriſt. The one ſort are more beholden to their natural or acquired Abilities, the other to the inward and effectual workings of the Holy Spirit. Every Perſon who hath a true ſenſe, and firm perſwaſion of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Matters, hath not the Gift of Ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance. There is no neceſſity a true
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:43210:43"/>and ſound Believer ſhould be eloquent, or have a voluble Tongue. Much Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, and Memory, and Utterance, and lively Affection, (as a worthy reverend Perſon hath ſaid) are all very deſirable; but you muſt judg your Eſtate by none of thoſe, for they are all uncertain.</p>
            <p>And who-ever truly receives Chriſt, will acknowledg and profeſs his owning of Chriſt. For as Men <hi>believe with the Heart, ſo with the Mouth confeſſion is made unto Salvation,</hi> Rom. 10.10.</p>
            <p>But now I come to ſpeak more poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively to this Point. Our receiving of Chriſt is expreſſed in my Text by theſe words; <hi>If any Man hear my Voice, and open the Door.</hi> So that two things are required to, and imported, by our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of Chriſt, according to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Letter of the Text;</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1ſt,</hi> Hearing his Voice.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> Opening unto him.</item>
            </list>
            <p>But before I ſpeak particularly to theſe things, let me obſerve to you, from the general indefinite Expreſſion here uſed, That Jeſus Chriſt doth not exclude any one Perſon from enjoying
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:43210:43"/>Him, and the Benefits of his Death and gracious Preſence, provided he will but comply with Him, and accept of his gracious Offers. He is willing to come to, and dwell with any Perſon who will but hearken to his Voice, and give Him admittance. He will not refuſe you for any perſonal unworthineſs, or becauſe you have been very grievous and noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Tranſgreſſors. He <hi>would have all Men to be ſaved, and come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the Truth,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.4. He in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites all without exception, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1, 2. <hi>If any Man hear my Voice;</hi> any Man, though ever ſo poor or miſerable in the Eye of the World; nay, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he hath been ever ſo violent and fierce againſt me, though his Sins be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo many, never ſo great, never ſo hainou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, yet if he will but hear my Voice, obey my Call, and open unto me, I will accept of him, I will be his Gueſt, and impart unto him my Self, my Merits, and the Comforts, Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions, and Benefits ariſing therefrom. We have very ſignal Evidences of this in the Holy Scriptures. <hi>Peter</hi> after his moſt deteſtable denial of Chriſt, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into Favour. <hi>Paul,</hi> though he
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:43210:44"/>had been ſuch an outragious Perſecutor, findeth Mercy, and is made a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and uſeful Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>The general Doctrine of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth confirm this Truth, That Chriſt is ready and willing to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Himſelf, and the Benefits of his Death and Paſſion, to any that will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of him. Chriſt hath put no Bar, no Impediment, no Hindrance in any Man's way. If we do not accept of Him, if we reap not the Benefits of his Death, the fault is our own, even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we would not receive Him when he came unto us, and entreated for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance. He comes to, and ſeeks af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the moſt unworthy, <hi>Mark</hi> 2.17. He came to ſave Sinners, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. He came to ſeek and to ſave the Loſt. He excepts none, if they renounce their Wickedneſſes and Sins, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.7.</p>
            <p>The Terms he propoſeth to us, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to our reaping all this Advantage, are but hearing his Voice, and opening the Door.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1ſt,</hi> Hearing his Voice. This imports two things.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:43210:44"/>1. Attending to, and taking notice of thoſe Arguments he doth urge to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain admittance. I have given you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a ſhort account of theſe Arguments. But this inſtructs us, that an heedful at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive frame of Spirit, is ordinarily requiſite to a due receiving of Chriſt into our Hearts. An unruly froward temper, that is impatient of Spiritual Advice, Inſtruction, Reproof, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and fumes and chafes on all ſuch occaſions, and applies to any ſort of courſes to divert from ſerious conſiderations, is a very dangerous and unhappy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
            <p>But this is not all that hearing Chriſt's Voice doth import. People may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to Matters of this nature, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign no more than to obtain ſome em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliſhments in their Diſcourſe; or they may have ſome deſign not truly uſeful and commendable. Indeed, God may make his Word to faſten, and prove effectual to thoſe who have none of the beſt purpoſes in hearkning to the Word of Chriſt; and therefore I dare not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage any Man abſolutely from at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending, whatever he may propoſe to himſelf in ſo doing, becauſe the Word
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:43210:45"/>may take hold of him beyond expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Bilney</hi> reports of himſelf, that he bought and read the New Teſtament, not becauſe it was the Word of God, but becauſe <hi>Eraſmus</hi> had tranſlated it into excellent Latin; yet it pleaſed God, when he read 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. that his Mind was particularly fixed on thoſe words; ſo that God made them effectual for his Converſion and Reformation.</p>
            <p>But ſuch Inſtances are ſomething out of the uſual and common road; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have reaſon to conclude, that hearkning to the Voice of Chriſt, doth note ſomething more than bare atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance to his Voice.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It doth note the Influence the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments our Saviour doth uſe, have on our Affections and Hearts. Attention is a very uſeful Expedient for the making of thoſe things which are propoſed unto us, to have ſome efficacy on us. When we diligently attend to any thing that is ſpoken, we have Impreſſions or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily made on our Minds, which bear ſome proportion with what hath been diſcourſed. And this ſeems to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported here by hearing Chriſt's Voice;
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:43210:45"/>thoſe Impreſſions, which the ſerious conſidering what he hath propos'd, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to be faſtned on our Hearts and Minds, the Affections and Diſpoſitions of Soul, which do reſult from our heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to his Voice. Which is ſomething betwixt bare hearing his Voice, and opening unto him. It is the Reſult, Fruit, and Conſequent of the former, and a good and proper Preparative to the latter.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly,</hi> Opening the Door. This is the other Expreſſion in the Text, to note our receiving of Chriſt. And it doth import our compliance with him, our free and ſincere reſignation of our ſelves unto him. As a Perſon, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in an Houſe, when another who is the right owner of it, comes and knocks at the Door, and declares to the Party within his claim to that Houſe, and makes it appear he is the true owner of that Houſe, and has Authority to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the Poſſeſſion to be delivered up unto him; the Party within hearkning to what he hath to ſay, and being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, and fully ſatisfied of his Right and Authority to make that Demand,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:43210:46"/>he opens the Door to him, and admits him into the Houſe; not only in point of common civility, but ſo as owning his Propriety, and delivering up the Poſſeſſion to him. Thus opening to Chriſt, doth note our giving up our Hearts to him, and owning him for the only, true, lawful Soveraign, Owner, and Governour of them. Our receiving Chriſt is not right, till we arrive at this Point. People may give attendance to Chriſt's Voice, and have their Affections and Hearts in ſome meaſure moved and influenced by the ſame, and yet Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption may prevail and keep them from reſigning up the Poſſeſſion to him. Nay, it falls out too often thus with the truly Godly, that they do not immediately, upon ſome affection and ſence begot in them, upon their hearing the Voice of their Saviour, reſign up themſelves, and comply with his Demands as they ſhould. The Spouſe, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.2, 4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> heard the Voice of her Beloved; ſhe knew it to be his Voice, and ſeemed to attend to what he ſaid, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. And though ſhe made ſeveral Excuſes, yet we may eaſily perceive his Voice had ſome influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence on her. Ver. 4. <hi>My Bowels were moved
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:43210:46"/>for him.</hi> Yet notwithſtanding all this, ſhe did not open unto him. He was provoked to withdraw, and went his way, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>But I will not confine my ſelf ſtrictly to a minute enquiry into the extent of theſe Phraſes uſed in the Text. I ſhall give you my ſenſe of what our receiving Chriſt doth import, in a few Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, where you will have the Subſtance of what is contained in, or implied by theſe Expreſſions in the Text.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Our receiving of Chriſt, doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our having a deep and affectionate ſenſe of the Danger, Evil, and Filth of Sin, and in what an undone condition we are naturally. We are not fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Chriſt into our Hearts, till we have an entire, hearty, and invincible dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation and abhorrence of Sin, which is ſo contrary to Chriſt, ſetled in our Souls. We cannot prize and value Chriſt aright, till we are ſenſible how hateful and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Sin is. Chriſt and Sin cannot reign together, nay, they cannot ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cably lodg together in the ſame Soul. We cannot ſerve God and <hi>Mammon.</hi> If we do not ſee our ſelves loſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done without Chriſt, we cannot bid him
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:43210:47"/>truly welcome. The Phyſician is not look'd after, nor regarded, till we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive our Diſtemper, and are ſenſible how weak and uneaſy it makes us, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.12. <hi>Paul</hi> ſees himſelf the greateſt Sinner, before he obſerves and takes comfort in the lovelineſs of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. Thoſe whom Chriſt calls and incourageth to come to him, are they who are preſſed and grieved with the weight and burthen of their Sins, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28.</p>
            <p>Now, do you try and examine your ſelves, whether you are duly affected with the evil and ſilth of Sin, with your deplorable and loſt Eſtate whilſt out of Chriſt? Do you really think that there is nothing in the World near ſo perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, evil, and hateful, as Sin? Is Sin more hateful to you than Hell? Can you truly chuſe the greateſt Suffering and Miſery, rather than commit the leaſt Sin knowingly againſt God and Chriſt? Are you brought to this Point, to ſay in ſincerity, All for Chriſt? Haſt thou ſuch a ſence of Sin, as makes thee cry out in holy Reſignation; Lord, what wilt thou have me to do? What ſhall I do to be ſaved?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:43210:47"/>2. Our receiving of Chriſt, doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port a firm belief of his Divinity, and the alſufficiency of his Merits and Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. A ſinful Creature, who is loſt and undone in himſelf, and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends his own Eſtate, would catch at every thing, but knows not where to fix, till he be indued with a truly Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Faith, and thereby has his Mind throughly ſatisfied, that the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the only begotten Son of God, is appointed by the Father, to be <hi>a Propitiation for the Sins of the World;</hi> and that he having obeyed and ſuffered, according to the Agreement betwixt Him and the Father, is alſufficient for the ſaving of all thoſe who do believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly cloſe with him. A meer cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary aſſent to what is ſaid of Chriſt in Scripture, will not ſerve our turn. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan will eaſily baffle and overcome ſuch a Faith. It muſt be ſuch an inward aſſent and conſent, as carries all the Powers of the Soul along with them; ſuch a Faith as is impregnated and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in us by the Power of the Holy Ghoſt. The Heart muſt be firmly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of Chriſt's being the Son of God; that he hath made full ſatisfaction
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:43210:48"/>to God's Juſtice, and that in him there is a compleat and abſolute fulneſs for us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25.</p>
            <p>Do you therefore examine your ſelves concerning your preſent Eſtate, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire whether you have a ſure and firm Belief wrought in you, that Chriſt is God, and that he is a compleat and perfect Saviour, that <hi>in him dwelleth all Fulneſs;</hi> and that notwithſtanding your own perſonal unworthineſs, yet you may and ſhall, if you believingly and obediently depend on him, be accepted, for his Merits and Worthineſs? I do not ſpeak of a ſuperficial Aſſent, a meer notional Belief, but ſuch a Faith as is a living active Principle in us, which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermines and ſupplants our Luſts, and mortifieth them daily in us, and puts us with vigor and earneſtneſs on all Acts of Holy Obedience, and faithfully en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to pleaſe God. Are you firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded, on Scripture-Grounds, that Jeſus Chriſt is the Son of God; <hi>That there is no other Name given under Heaven, by which you can be ſaved;</hi> and that in him there is ſuch a redundancy, that <hi>of his Fulneſs you may receive Grace for Grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:43210:48"/>3. Our receiving Chriſt doth import, our laying on him the great and only ſtreſs of our Salvation; our looking up to him, and depending on him alone for Pardon, Life, and Happineſs. If we will receive Chriſt, we muſt deny, not only our ſinful worldly Luſts, but we muſt deny our ſelves, as to our beſt and moſt religious Duties, Works, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances. We muſt not deſiſt from, and break off from theſe Performances, but we muſt deny them, ſo as not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend and rely on them, as if by the Worthineſs and Merit of theſe, we could purchaſe Life and Salvation to our ſelves. Though it is our duty to work and labour in the Service of God, with ſuch earneſtneſs and diligence, as if we were to get Heaven by our own pains; yet when we have done all, we muſt rely wholly on the Satisfaction, Righteouſneſs, and Merits of Chriſt. A true Believer will have his Eye on Chriſt, when at Duty, to engage his Fervency and Diligence; and after he hath done all he can, he will rely only upon him for acceptance. When we have done all we can, we muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg our ſelves <hi>unprofitable Servants,</hi> Luk. 17.10.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:43210:49"/>
            <p>Now, haſt thou learn'd to deny thy ſelf? Do'ſt thou not pleaſe thy ſelf, that becauſe thou art not as prophane and looſe as many others are, that for this cauſe thou ſhalt be accepted and ſaved? Alas, bare Morality will lodg Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple far ſhort of Heaven. Do'ſt thou not conclude thy Condition good and ſafe enough, becauſe thou prayeſt often, readeſt the Scriptures, heareſt the Word preached, and partakeſt of the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper, as occaſion offereth? Alas, if thou relieſt on theſe things, thou wilt find thy ſelf but in the ſtate of Hypocrites, and of thoſe ſpoken of in <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.21, 22, 23.</p>
            <p>Do'ſt thou not think thou muſt needs go to Heaven, for thy pious Services, thy good Works, and thy Charity in relieving the Poor? If ſo, read what the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3. He that receiveth Chriſt into his Heart, goes wholly out of himſelf to Chriſt. He lays no ſtreſs on any thing he can do. He labours after the greateſt conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty he can attain to, the Will of God, and doth this out of obedience to God; but when he hath prayed with the greateſt fervency he can, and hath expreſſed
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:43210:49"/>the greateſt Zeal for God and Religion he can reach unto; when he hath done all within his Power, he renounces all thoughts of Merit in himſelf, and flies only to Chriſt for favour and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. He is ſenſible of his own Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and Infirmities, and cries out againſt himſelf, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean, unclean!</hi> my <hi>beſt Righteouſneſſes are but as filthy Rags;</hi> I am but <hi>an unprofitable Servant.</hi> He haſtneth to Chriſt to undertake for him; and cries out, Bleſſed Jeſus, let thy Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and Satisfaction obtain acceptance and favour for me. Lord, I throw my ſelf into the Arms of thy Grace; O, reject me not, but grant I may be found in thee, and may have thy Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to commend me.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Our receiving Chriſt doth note, our complying with his Terms. Moſt would be willing to be ſaved at laſt, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided they might have liberty to live as they liſt at preſent. But Chriſt muſt be accepted on his own Terms; He calls us to Repentance, Faith, and new Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. If we will conclude on good ground, that we have received Chriſt, we muſt ſee to it, that we ſincerely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake our former Luſts and Sins, which
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:43210:50"/>ſo long ſeparated betwixt us and our God, and for which Chriſt did under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go and ſuffer ſuch preſſing and aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing Sorrows and Puniſhments. <hi>Let the Wicked forſake his Way, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Man his Thoughts,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.7. We muſt believe in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that he is the Son of God; that out of pure Love he did aſſume our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; that he hath performed all that is neceſſary to put us into a capacity of Salvation, and to reconcile us unto God, that he is the only Author of Eternal Life and Salvation. And we muſt rely and depend upon him only for Mercy and Salvation. We muſt devote our ſelves to live godly, righteouſly, and ſoberly, and make Conſcience of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to, and walking in all Chriſt's Commandments. And we muſt take care to get all this cleared and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced to our ſelves from Scripture-Grounds.</p>
            <p>Art thou truly willing to part with all thy Luſt! to mortify thy corrupt Affections, and to die every day more and more to ſin! to be crucified to the World, and to oppoſe and reſiſt all that fights againſt thy Soul? Do'ſt thou la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:43210:50"/>to exerciſe Faith vigorouſly? is it thy Buſineſs to eye Chriſt continually? do'ſt thou fetch all thy Strength and Supplies from Him? are all thy Hopes and Expectations laid up in him? do'ſt thou, without any reſervation, give up thy ſelf to Chriſt! is it thy heartieſt deſire, ſtudy, care, and endeavour, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to imitate and pleaſe Chriſt?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Our receiving Chriſt doth import, our ſubmitting to him in all his Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. It was a great Reflection on ſome who followed Chriſt, when he was here upon Earth, that they <hi>followed him for the Loaves with which he fed them,</hi> and <hi>not for the Miracles which they ſaw him work;</hi> whereby his Divinity was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted, and the Truth of the Doctrines he taught, undeniably evidenced and confirmed. And it would be as ſevere a Reflection upon us, ſhould Chriſt lay it to our Charge, that though we pretend to ſubmit to Him in one Relation, yet we refuſe to own and acknowledg Him in his other Relations. That we are willing to admit him to be our Prieſt, to ſuffer for us, but will not have any thing to do with his Yoke, but do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely caſt his Laws behind our back,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:43210:51"/>and determine that we will not have him to reign over us.</p>
            <p>But it is our Duty to be ready and willing, for his ſake, to take up the Croſs, as well as to wear the Crown; to ſubmit to do his Work, as well as to expect and receive the Recompences and Wages he doth beſtow. We muſt take him as our King, as our Husband, as our Lord, and as our Owner, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to him all thoſe Duties which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern us, as we are his Subjects, his Spouſe, his Servants and People, in whom he hath an undeniable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty.</p>
            <p>We ſhould complain to Chriſt of our hard and inflexible Hearts, our unruly and tumultuous Affections, of thoſe Luſts and Wickedneſſes which we find ſtrongeſt in us, we ſhould be earneſt with him in deſiring his powerful governing Preſence in and with us, that our Luſts may be conquered, our Affections ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, made moderate and ſanctified; and that our ſtubborn Hearts may be made ſoft and pliable.</p>
            <p>We muſt take him for our Prieſt, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting nothing but Wrath, as what is due to what we can do of our ſelves,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:43210:51"/>and therefore relying wholly on Chriſt. We muſt not look for any Pardon, but what Chriſt's Blood hath purchaſed, nor any fellowſhip and communion with God, but what Chriſt doth by his inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion obtain for us.</p>
            <p>We muſt take him for our Prophet, to teach, direct, and guide us, and to adviſe and counſel us. We are naturally ignorant of God, and our ſelves, and the things which moſt of all concern us; and we cannot get a ſound and perfect knowledg of them, but by his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, who is the great Revealer of them, even Jeſus Chriſt as Prophet. Thoſe who will receive Chriſt aright, muſt learn to know and underſtand his Voice and Dialect, that whenſoever they hear it, they may <hi>follow him,</hi> John 10.4. Chriſt is <hi>the Truth, the Way, and the Life;</hi> and there is no coming to, or knowing of the Father, but by him, <hi>John</hi> 14.6. We muſt take him for our great Teacher; we muſt be willing to learn whatever he ſhall inſtruct us in, and embrace and receive every direction he ſhall give us.</p>
            <p>Conſider therefore with your ſelves, whether it be thus with you: Whether
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:43210:52"/>you have ſincerely given up your ſelves to his Government, do willingly ſubmit to his Laws, do chearfully conſent that he ſhould rule over you? Do you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend only on his Sacrifice and Merits? and do you rejoice in his Light? Do you receive him as a Maſter, a Father, a Brother, a Friend? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And do you demean your ſelves to him in all the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Offices of your Relations, as by the Obligations ariſing from ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, you are bound unto? <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.6.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Our receiving Chriſt into our Hearts, doth import our having a tranſcendent and extraordinary love for Chriſt. No Man is worthy to follow Chriſt, or be owned by him, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny himſelf, and take up his Croſs for his ſake. Chriſt will not take up his abode in that Heart, which is not entirely given up and reſigned to him. Our loving other things, either with an equal or a greater Love than what we have for Chriſt, renders us wholly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to enjoy him, and deprives us of thoſe ſpecial Communications he would otherwiſe vouchſafe unto us. When Chriſt comes to us, and calls for admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:43210:52"/>he comes not like a Stranger to ſtay for a little while, but as a Friend, nay an Owner, to take up his fixed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence, and make his conſtant abode with us. A little outward Ceremony, and common Courteſy, doth ſuffice for the entertainment of ſuch as make Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits accidentally, or for whom there is no very great reſpect. But Love is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, that there may be a perſonal conſtant abode, and a mutual friendly converſe together. Chriſt muſt have our whole Hearts, he cannot endure a Rival. If we love other things, it muſt be for his ſake, and in ſubordination to him, or elſe this will exclude him, and evidence that we refuſe to receive him.</p>
            <p>Call your ſelves now to an account, and ſee whether your Hearts are free, and diſengaged from all other things; or whether you are willing to receive Chriſt, according to this ſenſe of the Phraſe. Can you ſay, in ſincerity, Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Jeſus, my only and moſt beloved Saviour, here is my whole Heart, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign it entirely unto thee? I deſire no greater, nor no other happineſs, than that thou wilt be pleaſed to make it thy
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:43210:53"/>Temple, the place of thy gracious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence: It is my earneſt requeſt, and ſhall be my diligent endeavour, to have it cleanſed and made pure, from every Affection and Inclination, which is any way contrary to thy Purity and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. O, do thou be pleaſed to give in thy aſſiſtance! diſpoſe and prepare my Soul to thy own mind! and, bleſſed Lord, take full poſſeſſion of me, dwell in my Heart, and rule over my whole Man! Canſt thou truly ſay; Lord, <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but thee? and there is none upon Earth I deſire beſides thee,</hi> Pſal. 73.25. Do'ſt thou not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to know any thing <hi>but Jeſus Chriſt and him crucified?</hi> 1 Cor. 2.2. Do'ſt thou love Chriſt more than all the World? more than all thy Relations? more than all thoſe things which are commonly eſteemed the great Endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this World, yea, more than Life it ſelf? <hi>Luke</hi> 14.26. Jeſus Chriſt is very precious unto them who believe, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7. Now, canſt thou, for the ſake of Chriſt, deny thy Luſts, thy Self, thy beſt and moſt religious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances? Canſt thou live for Chriſt, and canſt thou ſuffer, yea, die for
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:43210:53"/>Chriſt? and is Chriſt above all in thy Heart?</p>
            <p>Thus you have ſome little account what kind of reception it is the Lord Jeſus doth call for, or what our receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt doth import. It would be too great a digreſſion here, to inſiſt on ſuch Conſiderations as are proper to evince it to be our Intereſt, and that we are under indiſpenſible Obligations to yield up our ſelves in this manner unto him. Much might be ſaid to this purpoſe, from the Excellencies of our Saviour, how precious he is in himſelf, how wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in his Condeſcenſion unto us, and what unvaluable Benefits and Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges do accrue unto Believers from Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But having on other Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions diſcourſed of theſe Matters more diſtinctly, I wave the conſideration of them now, haſtning to what I promiſed to take notice of in the third place: Only by the way we may obſerve, there is not any thing impli'd in what I have ſaid concerning our receiving of Chriſt, which can in the leaſt countenance our refuſal, or juſtly diſcourage us from complying with his Calls and Entreaties.
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:43210:54"/>And what ſhall the Eternal God, our only Saviour, importune us with all ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs, and we harden our ſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, reſiſt and reject him! in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, we ſhall be uncivil, ungrateful, to the higheſt degree impious againſt God, inhumane and barbarous to our power againſt Chriſt, and actually ſo to our own Souls; we ſhall be guilty of all that's Evil, of all that can deſerve an hateful, an ignominious, reproachful Name.</p>
            <p>Indeed, if Mens ordinary practices did not fully and undeniably evidence, that they have no real value for Chriſt, and that they do ſtubbornly refuſe to cloſe with his Calls, we might, when meditating on this Subject, be very apt to imagine and conclude, that none could be ſo undutiful, or ſo forgetful of themſelves, or ſo fooliſh, ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractedly-fond and ambitious of Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, as to purchaſe it, by a ſtubborn hardening themſelves againſt the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful affectionate perſwaſions of the Son of God, and a contemptuous deſpiteful throwing the gracious Offers, the very Blood and tendereſt Mercies of a loving, compaſſionate, Divine Saviour, back in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his own Face.</p>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:43210:54"/>
            <p>But alas! People every where, give too many and too frequent Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in the courſe of their Lives, of their diſaffection to Chriſt, and how little influence his Love hath on them. For this is certain, where Jeſus Chriſt doth reſide by his gracious Preſence, there will be a vigorous and active Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Grace and Holineſs, which will manifeſt it ſelf in the outward Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. When Chriſt is received into the Heart, doth ſettle his Abode there, and doth command and govern there, that Perſon with whom it is thus, will be poſſeſſed with ſuch a lively working Principle of Purity, Righteouſneſs, and Goodneſs, as will have a moſt powerful influence on all the parts of his Life.</p>
            <p>It is indeed a very deplorable thing, that amongſt ſo many pretenders to Chriſtianity, with which the World doth abound, is even throng'd and crowded, there ſhould be ſo few who give any ſerious, real attendance to the Voice of Chriſt, who give any tolerable diſcovery, that they have opened their Hearts to receive him.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:43210:55"/>III. Let us now therefore, in the third place, enquire after ſome of thoſe lets and hindrances, which keep our Hearts ſhut againſt Chriſt. Many might be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, but I will only take a brief no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of theſe few.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Carnal Pride, and Spiritual Self-conceitedneſs. People are generally ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unwilling to believe their condition ſo bad and helpleſs as naturally it is. It goes againſt Mens Spirits and Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machs, to think ſo meanly of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as not to be able to do any thing to recover, ſecure, and ſave themſelves. They would fain find ſome prop or other in themſelves to lean upon. Indeed they would be their own Phyſicians, and their own Saviours; and are very difficultly driven out of their carnal ſelfiſh Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. They will either pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with an opinion that they have no Wound; or if they muſt own that, they will find a Plaiſter for it at Home, they cannot in this caſe endure to go abroad for help. Corrupt Nature is very proud; we are hardly brought to deny our Selves, and to think ſo meanly of our Selves, our Works, our Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:43210:55"/>our religious Duties, as to be willing to be ſaved purely by free Grace. We would fain have ſome ſhare in this great Work our ſelves, we would have our own Wings to carry us to Heaven; At leaſt, we would have our own Works, and Religious Performances, to have ſome portion of the Glory. Men would be contented to have Chriſt's Hand and Arm to help them out of the Ditch, provided they may come out with ſome credit; that though there was a fall, and ſome dirt in the caſe, yet vigor and ſtrength continued, and they were able, with a very little help, to recover themſelves. Their Power (as they will have it) was ſufficient, they only wanted a Staff or Cord to hold by, that ſo they might exert that ability and ſtrength they had in themſelves.</p>
            <p>As Pride did at firſt put Man upon aſpiring to be as God, ſo now it doth tempt him to uſurp the Honour belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Son of God. Man would be his own Saviour, yea, his own God. He cannot endure to ſtoop, to drink of the Waters of Life. But as God and <hi>Mammon,</hi> Light and Darkneſs, ſo Chriſt
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:43210:56"/>and carnal proud Self cannot dwell and agree together.</p>
            <p>When the Goſpel was firſt preached about in the World, it was pride and ſelfiſhneſs which did moſt oppoſe it, and reſiſt Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.3. They were all for eſtabliſhing their own Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs. When the Chriſtian Religion was firſt recovered from the Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Darkneſſes which had long overſpread it, the Reformation began in rectifying Mens Judgments and Minds about this Matter, of the inſufficiency of our own Works, and the abſolute neceſſity of the Righteouſneſs and Merits of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The <hi>high and lofty God,</hi> will dwell with none but thoſe <hi>who are of humble and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite Spirits,</hi> Iſa. 57.15. As long as we pleaſe our ſelves with fancying we have no need of Chriſt, we have a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency in our ſelves, and can do well enough without him, we ſhall never at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with due care to his Voice, nor faithfully receive him into our Hearts. We are apt to think our ſelves <hi>rich and increaſed with Goods,</hi> and that we have no need of any thing without us, and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:43210:56"/>are very difficultly perſwaded, that we <hi>are wretched, and miſerable, and poor, and blind, and naked,</hi> and therefore we ſlight Chriſt, and ſhut him out of our Hearts, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.17. There is no room for Chriſt, in a proud ſelf-conceited Heart.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Infidelity or Unbelief, doth keep the Heart ſhut againſt Chriſt. Herein conſiſts our non-acceptance of Chriſt. Notwithſtanding the Lord Jeſus hath ſo many Witneſſes, and explains himſelf to us ſo fully, yet do we ſlight and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject him. And whence is all this, but from our not diligently attending to his Inſtruction, nor underſtanding and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving aright of what he doth propoſe to us; not weighing and conſidering ſeriouſly the Evidence of things recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to us; not truly and really aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to the Truths of Chriſt? Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple content themſelves with empty No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and a faſhionable Profeſſion, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any real, firm perſwaſion of the Particulars they pretend to own. Did we really and firmly aſſent to, or believe the Doctrines concerning Chriſt, his Perſon, Natures, Offices, Promiſes,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:43210:57"/>Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> contained in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, we ſhould be thereby influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to a holy, faithful, entire recum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bency of Soul on Chriſt, and to a vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous active conformity to his Laws, and following of his Example. If there be no difference betwixt us, and Turks or Heathens, but only that we call our ſelves by another Name, and in word pretend to another Religion, we do not really believe: For Faith, if real, will influence our Affections and Lives, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably to the Degree of our Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, the Nature and Tendency of the Truths we do believe, and the Senſe we have of our concernment in them.</p>
            <p>It is the great Fault of People pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to Religion, and enjoying means of Inſtruction, that they do not take a becoming care to get their Minds poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with right and ſound Notions of the Truths and Doctrines they profeſs to own. They do not conſider what Grounds and Evidences they have, for their yielding aſſent to the Doctrines they profeſs; they do not labour and endeavour, and ſtrive to get the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of Divine Truths deeply im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed with their full Light and Power
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:43210:57"/>on their Hearts. And how can it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe be expected then, but that multitudes ſhould prove meer Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites and Formaliſts? It is Unbelief that blinds our Minds, that we ſee no beauty or lovelineſs in Chriſt; it is this that turns away our Hearts from Chriſt, renders us uncapable of receiving any ſaving benefit from Chriſt, which har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens and ſears our Conſciences, makes them unſenſible, and locks and bolts our Hearts againſt Chriſt. See <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.2, 3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.12. <hi>John</hi> 1.11, 12. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.58. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.20, 22, 23.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Worldly-mindedneſs keeps the Heart ſhut againſt Chriſt. When we expect too much from the World, and theſe lower Enjoyments, do ſet our Hearts exceſſively on them, preſs after, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue and ſeek for earthly Things, with too much vehemence and earneſtneſs, we, of courſe, grow unmindful of, and unconcerned for Chriſt and our Souls, Heaven and Spiritual Matters. The Things of the World do devour our Strength, and drink up all our Spirits: yea, they beget in us, not only a regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs of Spiritual Things, but a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:43210:58"/>of, and oppoſition againſt them. <hi>Know ye not, that the Friendſhip of the World is Enmity with God: whoſoever therefore will be a Friend of the World, is the Enemy of God,</hi> Jam. 4.4. ſee 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.15. Alas! when Mens Hearts are ſet upon the World, what will they not venture for it? They venture Chriſt, and Heaven, and Soul, and all that is truly precious. This worldly-minded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, makes the Word and Truths of Chriſt to be of no eſteem and value with us, this makes them of no uſe to us, makes us that we reap no benefit from them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.22. How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who have made a fair ſhew in the Fleſh, have ſeemed to make fair Offers for Chriſt, have fallen off as ſoon as ever they have been tried as to this Point! ſee <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.22. The love of this preſent World, choak'd and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd <hi>Demas,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.10. What a curſed influence had the love of the World on <hi>Judas,</hi> when he adventured on that villanous piece of Treachery, to betray and ſell his Lord and Maſter, the Son of God, for thirty pieces of Silver!</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:43210:58"/>4. Love of carnal ſenſual Pleaſures. We read of ſome who are <hi>lovers of Pleaſures more than lovers of God,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.4. Of ſome who make their Belly their God, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19. Now, ſuch as have devoted themſelves to their Luſts, and are wholly enſlaved to their Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and ſenſual Delights, are wholly indiſpos'd and unfit to bid Chriſt wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come. There muſt be a great change wrought in them, before they can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and entertain Chriſt. It is not meet to bring a Perſon of Honour and Quality into a Room that is full of Vomit and loathſom filthineſs and ſtench: Such a Perſon will not be entertained and treated in a Swine-ſtye: and the Heart of him that wallows in his ſinful Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures is no better. That Soul where Chriſt will dwell, muſt be cleanſed from all thoſe <hi>fleſhly Luſts which war againſt the Soul,</hi> Rom. 13.14. And as ſuch a Heart is very unfit for Chriſt, ſo there is much malignity in it againſt Chriſt. Who greater Enemies to Chriſt, and who ſo bitter againſt his Ways, his Laws, his Word, his Government, than thoſe who do wholly addict themſelves
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:43210:59"/>to the ſenſual gratifying of all their carnal Appetites, Deſires, and Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions! If they may not enjoy their ſwi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Luſts, without any moleſtation and reproof from Chriſt and his Word, they will either, with the <hi>Gadarens,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire them to be gone, or elſe more rudely attempt to thruſt and force them out of their Quarters.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Cheriſhing any particular Luſt or Sin in our Hearts, and ſuffering it to have a predominant reigning Power over us. Though we ſeem to reject and caſt from us many of our former Vices, and to deny our ſelves in ſeveral Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in which we did before allow our ſelves a greater liberty, yet if we yield up our ſelves Subjects to any one Sin, though we do it never ſo cunningly and ſecretly, we do thereby bid Chriſt defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and renounce his Rule and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment over us. If a Man make his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to one he deſires to have a conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal friendſhip and familiarity with; if that Party have preingaged her ſelf faithfully to another Perſon, this is a more effectual Impediment to his admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, than if he had a multitude of
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:43210:59"/>Rivals. If we cheriſh any one Luſt in our Boſom, and ſuffer it to rule there, it will as certainly keep Chriſt out of our Hearts, as if we did allow our ſelves in a greater number of Sins. If we were only haunted by Sin, belea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guer'd and ſet upon, courted and ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited, though by hundreds of Luſts, the caſe would not be deſperate; we might, it may be, ſooner liſten to Chriſt, than to any of them: but when we cloſe with any Luſt, ſubmit our ſelves to its Power, take it into our Heart, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throne and crown it there, chuſing and preferring it before Chriſt, then is our caſe dangerous indeed, though we ſeem to reject and offer ſome indignity to thoſe other Luſts and Vices that were ſuing for entertainment, but did not ſuit ſo well with our Humor and Fancy, as that did which we have ſurrendred our ſelves unto.</p>
            <p>Too many do pretend to receive Chriſt, and yet exclude him this way. They are deſcribed, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.5. <hi>That ſwear by the Lord, and that ſwear by Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cham;</hi> that is, they profeſs friendſhip, and ſubjection, and obedience unto
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:43210:60"/>God; and bind themſelves hereunto, by the ſtrongeſt ties that can be deviſed, ſwearing to be true and faithful to him alone, and yet under-hand they ſwear to <hi>Malcham; i.e.</hi> they ſwear in the ſame manner, and devote themſelves by Oath to be true to <hi>Moloch.</hi> Take heed you do not entertain, indulge, or ſet up any Luſt in your Hearts, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo privately, for if you do, this will keep Chriſt out, and you will be as guilty before him, as thoſe who did ſwear by <hi>Malcham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IV. We are now, in the fourth place, to enquire why Jeſus Chriſt doth uſe ſo much importunity with Sinners to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of him?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Chriſt doth not uſe this earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with us, as though he ſtood in any need of us. It is not to acquire any advantage or benefit to himſelf from us, but for our ſakes, and for our good, that we may reap thoſe Satisfactions which ſpring from Peoples enjoying of him. He is abſolutely perfect, and doth not need any thing from us. As he is
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:43210:60"/>God, he was eternally bleſſed before we were in being. And if we conſider him as Man, the humane Nature is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceivably bleſſed, in that perſonal Union it is admitted unto with the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine. Thoſe glorious Diſcoveries which are made to him, thoſe bleſſed Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications which are imparted to the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature, and that unintelligible intimacy there is betwixt the two Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, do enrich him as Man, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible ſatisfactions and felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p>Indeed, if we conſider Chriſt with reference to the Relation he bears to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, and the number of God's Elect, and how his Myſtical Body is not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, till the whole number be effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally called and brought together unto him, we may perceive ſomething there which may ſomewhat illuſtrate his ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs in importuning Sinners to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with his gracious Offers, for herein we take notice of him in the execution of his Office. And for this very end it is, amongſt others, that he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed ſeveral Offices in his Church, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11, 12, 13. But what we are
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:43210:61"/>chiefly to refer his earneſtneſs and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, unto what we may impute it to, with greateſt ſafety and aſſurance, is divine, free, and undeſerved Love.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He doth not uſe this earneſtneſs with Sinners, as though he could not procure himſelf admittance without their concurrence. God ordinarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth our concurrence, even as to thoſe Inſtances wherein he doth moſt wonderfully diſplay and magnify the Riches of his Grace towards us; not as if we our ſelves were to have the greateſt hand in the Work, or that it could not be effected, unleſs we did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ert our ſtrength for that purpoſe. But becauſe he will deal with us as with ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Creatures. He will not force and drive Men into Heaven and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs aginſt their wills. He proceeds in ſuch a way as is moſt proper to work upon our reaſonable Faculties; and he makes uſe of them for the perfecting of what he deſigns. He doth ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily make uſe of rational Expedients with Men; and if theſe prove unſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesful, thoſe Perſons are for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:43210:61"/>obſtinacy and ſtubbornneſs, juſtly rejected, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.11, 12.</p>
            <p>The Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath <hi>the Koy of</hi> David, <hi>he openeth and no Man ſhutteth,</hi> Rev. 3.7. He hath power over all Hearts, and can command admittance when he pleaſeth, but he thinks fit to uſe importunity, and to proceed in ſuch a way as is moſt ſuitable unto our Natures. And he doth thus;</p>
            <p n="1">1. To teſtify, with the greater force and evidence, his wonderful great Love to Sinners, how ready and willing he is to ſave them; He might ſay to Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, at the firſt repulſe they give him, <hi>Let the filthy be filthy ſtill, and let the unclean be unclean ſtill.</hi> But when he puts up many denials and affronts, and ſtill renews his earneſt Sollicitations, and ſtill condeſcends to argue and plead with Sinners, his Love muſt be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged on all hands, by all ſorts of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to be extraordinary great, and fit to win and conſtrain our Hearts to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to, and cloſe with his Tenders. O, what refractory, helpleſs, and even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiable Wretches are they, who will
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:43210:62"/>hurry themſelves to Hell in deſpite of all his Love! Miſerable and wilful Wretch, what canſt thou propoſe to thy ſelf, in rejecting and flying from the tenders of thy Saviour's Love? Canſt thou think to ſweeten and indear Damnation to thee, by preferring it before Life? The whole Work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and Salvation is founded on, and ſprings from Love; every Paſſage belonging to it, is a moſt great and pregnant demonſtration of Love. And in a very particular, even ſenſible man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, doth our Bleſſed Saviour diſcover, manifeſt, and approve the exceeding Riches and Greatneſs of his Love, in being ſo earneſt and importunate with Sinners for admittance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That all obſtinate and impenitent rejecters of Chriſt, and Grace, may be at laſt without any excuſe. He that ſtubbornly ſtands out againſt all the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Courtings, and loves his Luſts ſo immoderately, that he will not be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with by Chriſt, nor all his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties to renounce and forſake them, muſt needs be in a very forlorn and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:43210:62"/>dreadful ſtate. When the Lord Jeſus ſhall come to Judgment, what will that miſerable Wretch do? Sinner! thou wilt not have one word to ſay in thy own defence: Thou muſt ſtand aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, full of ſhame and confuſion, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and dumb, without any Apology and Excuſe. Nay, how loudly wilt thou then complain againſt, and upbraid and reproach thy ſelf, for thy paſt contempt, and mad refuſing of offered Grace and Mercy! How unmercifully and cruelly, to thy own unſpeakable vexation, wilt thou then roar forth thy ſenſe of thy approaching juſt Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
            <p>Some may think to make Apologies for themſelves, and pretend they were ignorant, they had not the Means, the Helps, the Opportunities others had, otherwiſe they would not have done as they did. But thou ſtubborn refuſer of Chriſt, whoſoever thou art, know thou for a certainty, thy Mouth will be ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. The Lord Jeſus will tell thee to thy Face, before Angels, Men, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, that thou art that wickeed Wretch with whom he was treating ſo long, and
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:43210:63"/>with ſo much earneſtneſs, but all in vain. Ungrateful contemptuous Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner! I did not only ſhed my Blood, and pour out my Soul unto death for thee, but I condeſcended to treat more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly with thy ſelf; I tendered thee all this Happineſs and Glory; I did entreat and perſwade, and beſeech thee to entertain me, and accept of the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, and Priviledges, and Mercies, the Graces, Felicities, and Inheritan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, purchaſed by my ſpotleſs and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Blood; I pleaded many Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with thee; I urged ſuch and ſuch Conſiderations to thy Soul and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; I did thus, not once, or twice, but for ſo many Years together, ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, ſo earneſtly, by ſo many and ſuch various means, but thou wouldſt not hear my Voice, thou didſt not open the Door to me, thou didſt finally reſolve to keep thy Heart ſhut againſt me. If thou hadſt hearkened to me, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived me into thy Heart, I would have made all my Promiſes good to thee, thou ſhouldſt have been for ever in this Bleſſed and Holy Society, inheriting that Glory and Happineſs, thoſe who did
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:43210:63"/>receive me are entred into. But what, thou ungrateful wicked Sinner, Self-deſtroying wilful Wretch, canſt thou now expect at my Hands! Haſt thou any thing to object why I ſhould not denounce and make good my formerly declared Threatnings againſt thee! O poor, miſerable, confounded Creature, how ſilent wilt thou ſtand! Whither wilt thou ſink under all the horrible miſgivings of thy own Soul, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable terrifying Accuſations, Reprimands, and Laſhes of thy enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged guilty Conſcience! and the weight and terror of all that fearful Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and dreadful Condemnation which is juſt coming upon thee! How will the Righteouſneſs and Juſtice of the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence which ſhall be paſt upon thee, be approved, owned, and witneſſed unto, by all that ſhall be there Spectators, both Angels, Men, and Devils!</p>
            <p>The Lord Jeſus will remove out of the way, all ſhew and appearance of excuſe. His pleading with us at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, if we receive him not, will be a dreadful Witneſs, and will make ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily againſt us at the laſt Day.
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:43210:64"/>
               <hi>If I had not come, and ſpoken unto them, they had not had Sin; but now they have no Cloak for their Sin,</hi> John 15.22.</p>
            <p n="5">V. Laſtly, We are, in the laſt place, to make ſome Application of what hath been diſcourſed. And,</p>
            <p n="1">1. We hence learn where Men muſt charge their own Deſtruction. You ſee how willing and ready God and Chriſt are, that you ſhould be ſaved. How earneſtly they entreat you to accept of Life, to fly from Wrath, and eſcape Damnation; read <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.31, 32. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.11. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. It is your own wilfulneſs and obſtinacy which muſt bear the blame. Men would fain charge God, or Chriſt, or any thing with their deſtruction, but themſelves. But alas! their Guilt will not be ſo eaſily ſhifted off, they themſelves are the moſt, if not only, faulty. God and Chriſt, do as much as we can modeſtly, as we can reaſonably deſire for our welfare. They do not take any pleaſure in our ruine; they offer Mercy, and intreat us to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it. Angels they are ready to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:43210:64"/>for our good; good Miniſters, and good People, deſire and labour all they can to prevent our Condemnation. Alas! none but wicked Men and Devils are pleaſed with, or dare knowingly help forward our Ruin and Damnation. But we our ſelves are the principal Cauſes and Authors of our own eternal unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.9. We keep Chriſt out of our Hearts, we will not liſten to his Calls, nor attend unto his Voice; we will not go to him that we may have Life; nor, we will not entertain him, when he comes himſelf unto us and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers us Life. We reſiſt his Motions, and oppoſe him in all the Inſtances of his Love. And what can we then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, but that he ſhould finally reject and diſown us?</p>
            <p n="2">2. We may hence obſerve the great ſenſleſneſs and ſtupidity Men are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally involved in. O! how hard and inſenſible is Man's Heart naturally! how do People live, even under the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Goſpel, as if they had no Souls, nor any Concerns relating to another World to attend unto! They
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:43210:65"/>mind not Chriſt, nor do they take any care to have their Hearts prepared for him. People are ſoon apprehenſive of temporal, corporal Dangers; but tho their Souls are every minute in danger, and Chriſt is calling to, and warning them, ſetting before them their hazard, and counſelling them to come to him, that they may be ſafe and ſecure, how idely and unconcernedly do they ſit, and take no notice at all of what is ſaid? O how hard muſt thoſe Hearts needs be, which will not, by all the Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, Eloquence, Affection, and Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs of the Son of God, be wrought on, prevailed with, or won over to a ſerious conſideration of another ſtate!</p>
            <p n="3">3. This ſhould encourage the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Jeſus Chriſt, to hold on pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently in the diſcharge of their Work, in earneſt importunate beſeeching Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to be reconciled unto God, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of Chriſt. It is indeed a great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, when a Man labours for nought, and when for his earneſtneſs and heartineſs in his Work, he is ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, reproached, and abuſed in the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:43210:65"/>World. And indeed, Miniſters find it hard to keep up their Spirits, and go on unweariedly in an uninterrupted renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their affectionate Entreaties, when they long perceive the Word trampled under-foot, and the moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious teſtimonies of ſpiritual, fervent deſire of Mens Salvation, deſpiſed and nick-named. Miniſters are too prone to deſpond, and to be dejected, when their Labours and Endeavours continue long without Succeſs, when they ſee Men remain as ſtubborn, and as violent oppoſers of Chriſt, after Inſtruction, Warnings, and multiplied vehement Entreaties and Perſwaſions, as they were before. It is heartleſs, nay, it is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting, and exceeding grievous to the Soul and Spirit of a true Goſpel-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, to have occaſion to cry out, <hi>Who hath believed our Report? and to whom is the Arm of the Lord revealed?</hi> Iſa. 53.1. But this ſhould not diſcourage, or make us deſiſt one jot from our moſt vigorous Importunity. For beſides that, <hi>Our Judgment is with the Lord, and our Work,</hi> or Recompence, <hi>is with our God,</hi> Iſa. 49.4.</p>
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:43210:66"/>
            <p>We have much incouragement, and obligation too, to perſiſt, from the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of our Bleſſed Maſter. If Chriſt himſelf doth wait long, and uſeth one Argument after another with Sinners, ſhould not we, who are but his Servants and Meſſengers, ſent to plead his Cauſe with Sinners, imitate him both in Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Importunity?</p>
            <p n="4">4. This may juſtly incourage poor Sinners to come to Chriſt, and to be earneſt and importunate in their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to the Throne of Grace. If the Lord Jeſus Chriſt do condeſcend thus to entreat and beſeech Sinners to receive him, no doubt but he will very gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly accept of, and receive thoſe who do come unto him; conſult <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1, 2, 3. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.1, 2.</p>
            <p>A returning Sinner, is the welcomeſt Gueſt to Jeſus Chriſt. What joy doth ſuch an one occaſion in Heaven! with what ſatisfaction did the Father receive and entertain the returning Prodigal! how do the glorious and bleſſed Spirits a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove rejoice, and ſing for gladneſs, when a Sinner forſakes his unrighteous
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:43210:66"/>Courſes, ſeeks after, and returns unto his Saviour, and ſincerely cloſeth with and embraceth him? <hi>Luke</hi> 15.7.</p>
            <p>And as Chriſt is importunate with us, ſo he would have us to be importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in our Applications unto him. He is very much pleaſed with our importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity at the Throne of Grace. When we inſiſt on what he hath done and ſuffered, when we plead his Office, and his Promiſes, and become ſo earneſt and vigorous in our Prayers and Wreſtlings, that we reſolve we will not let him go till he bleſſeth us. He ſometimes hides his Face, and ſeems to withhold his Ears from our Cries; but it is, that hereby he may awaken us from our chillineſs and deadneſs in the Duty, try our Love to himſelf, and quicken and engage us to a greater fervency in our Addreſſes. Nay, he ſeems to make this a neceſſary Requiſite to our coming to him acceptably, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.12.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Is the Lord Jeſus Chriſt very impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate with Sinners to receive &amp; entertain him; then let us all be hence perſwaded, and prevailed with to embrace and cloſe with his Motions. Do not reſiſt and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:43210:67"/>oppoſe him any longer, do not delay to open unto him, and give him that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception he calls for. Are you in love with Death! will you reſolve to court Damnation as ſollicitouſly, and with as much fervency, as you are entreated to accept of Chriſt and Salvation? What haſt thou, Sinner, to except againſt Chriſt? Why wilt thou add this, of ſturdy, inexcuſable, and moſt hideous fruſtrating the higheſt deſign of Love, in refuſing to accept of, and comply with an earneſt importunate Saviour, to all thy other Provocations? Art thou afraid thou ſhalt not ſink low enough into the bottomleſs Pit, nor find ſorrow and torment enough in Hell, unleſs thy contempt of Grace, and deſpiſing of Chriſt, may add weight to thy former Guilt, and make the unquenchable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal Flames more ſcorching, and to prey on thee with greater vehemence and fury! Sinner, Hell will be direfully black and terrible, the infernal Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments will inſupportably afflict and macerate; the loſs of Heaven, and the gracious preſence of the Divine Majeſty, will be inexpreſſibly dreadful
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:43210:67"/>and confounding, will fill with unſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable remorſe and horror, when they ſhall appear to be the Fruits of Mens wilfulneſs and choice. Exerciſe reaſon therefore once in thy Life, and hearken to Advice; Do not be ambitious to plunge thy ſelf into the utmoſt depth of Divine Indignation and Fury, by offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the moſt provoking contemptuous Affront to the Riches of God's Grace and Love: for, fancy thou, thy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, Strength, and Courage, to be never ſo great and invincible, yet the leaſt meaſure of Damnation will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently baffle and triumph over them: It will ſoon weary thee out, fill thee with ſuch horrors, and extort and force from thee ſuch dreadful howlings and ſhreiks, as will fully manifeſt thy Impatience is boundleſs, and thy Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry remedileſs.</p>
            <p>Sinner! why wilt thou reject the gracious Offers which thy Saviour makes thee? Why wilt thou deny him admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, when he tenders thee Himſelf, and all his Benefits? What better, what more deſirable Gueſt canſt thou have? Whether doſt thou think it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:43210:68"/>thy Heart ſhould be full of filthy diabolical Suggeſtions, and noiſom Luſts; or that thy Soul ſhould be the Temple of God, and be beautified and enriched with all ſorts of Graces and Divine Diſpoſitions?</p>
            <p>What is it then that keeps Chriſt out of thy Heart? What is it that makes thee unwilling to yield to thy Saviour's Importunity? produce thy ſhadowy vain pretences, and ſee how thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludeſt thy ſelf! Canſt thou value the Wealth and Riches of the World, more than the Son of God, who priz'd thee at ſuch a rate, as to lay down his Life for thee! certainly thou doſt eſteem them much above their worth, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs thou rectify this Miſtake in a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time, thou wilt make a very fooliſh bargain for thy ſelf.</p>
            <p>O ſtupid Sinner! awake, rouze up thy ſelf, ſhame thy ſelf out of thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cogitancy, folly, falſeneſs and ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude! Are the tranſitory, empty, counterfeited pleaſures of Sin, of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter value, and more precious to thee, than thoſe Rivers, thoſe Oceans of real tranſcendent ſatisfactions and delights
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:43210:68"/>which are in God's preſence, and at his right Hand! Can a periſhing uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain World, aſſure thee of better and more ſplendid entertainment than he can, who is over all, God bleſſed for ever, of whoſe fulneſs we all receive, and who filleth all in all! Are not the tranſports and raptures of Saints and Angels to be preferred before all thoſe groſs and fulſome Diverſions, carnal and fooliſh Men do ſo madly doat on? Canſt thou think it better, and more rationally deſirable, to be a Beaſt on Earth, than to be like one of the ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing glorious Seraphims, in the Regions of Light, and Peace, and Joy?</p>
            <p>Haſt thou any thing to except againſt the Terms thy Saviour doth propound? Doth he invite thee to any thing that is unreaſonable? doth he lay any bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then on thee, which is inſupportable, or unto which he will not adminiſter ſtrength proportionable? Thou canſt not pretend any thing of all this; what he requires, is almoſt obviouſly reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, juſt, good, and equal. And do's the Lord Jeſus call and importune thee to attend to the ſweeteſt Voice, and
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:43210:69"/>the moſt heavenly and raviſhing News that was ever made known: Do's he, who dwelleth in the higheſt Heavens, condeſcend to entreat for an abode with thee, that he may communicate Himſelf, and his Riches and Benefits to thee, in the freeſt and moſt friendly manner, and wilt thou yet reject him? O, how great muſt thy Guilt needs be! what an aggravation will this be, both of thy Sin, and Folly, and Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion!</p>
            <p>But to help thee a little more to quicken, and to make ſome impreſſion on thy Affections, let me propoſe theſe few Queſtions, and do thou perform thy Duty faithfully in anſwering them to thy own Conſcience ſincerely, and urging them impartially on thy own Soul.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt. <hi>1.</hi>
               </label> What art thou without Chriſt? O, Sinner, whilſt thou art in thy Sins, thou art no better than an Enemy to the great God of Heaven and Earth; a
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:43210:69"/>very Fire-brand of Hell, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.12. If thou hadſt the Plague broke on thee, or wert under any deſperate Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, how welcome would a Phyſician be to thee, who could infallibly cure and heal thee? Nay, what ſpeed wouldſt thou make in enquiring and ſearching out for ſuch an one, if thou couldſt hear of him? And what, ſhall thy Soul be under the worſt of Plagues, even the dominion of thy Luſts and Sins? Is thy condition ſuch, that thou art every minute in danger of having all the Vials of God's Wrath poured out upon thee, and wilt thou ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject thy Saviour, and ſturdily refuſe his help, when he only can adminiſter pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Remedies, and effect thy Cure and Deliverance?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt. <hi>2.</hi>
               </label> What haſt thou to truſt to, whilſt without Chriſt? Alas! all things but Chriſt, are broken, periſhing, afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reeds; ſuch Props, as if truſted to, will but deceive us, and make our fall the greater and more ruinous.
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:43210:70"/>Alas, Sinner! if thou hadſt all the World, its Power, its Wealth, its Glory; yea, if thou hadſt all the cunning and arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Hell too, theſe will not yield thee one jot of comfort or ſupply, when thy Want ſhall be greateſt and moſt urgent. O how ſad was it with that poor Soul, that having long ſlighted Chriſt, and deſpiſed Grace, being at laſt brought under the Laſhes and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations of an awakened condemning Conſcience, could take no reſt, receive no comfort, but was full of horror and black deſpair; when his Friends and Attendants ſpake to him of, applauded him for, and preſented before him the Honours and Preferments he had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the World, the Wealth and Eſtate he was maſter of, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred him of his paſt Pleaſures, the things he was wont to be moſt deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with, and endeavoured to divert him by Muſick, and other Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; all theſe proved inſipid, nay, vexatious. O, ſaid he, theſe I loved too much heretofore, they have been my bane, theſe wound and torment me! Theſe are not Chriſt! for theſe I
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:43210:70"/>ventur'd and fold my Soul, I prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them above Chriſt. Theſe inflame my grief, theſe wound me to the Heart, theſe imbitter and make my Life a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then to me; theſe kindle Hell in my Soul, theſe weigh and ſink me down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the bottomleſs Pit! I have no ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port at all, nothing to truſt to. There is none but Chriſt can do me good, or yield me help; and it is him I have deſpiſed and ſlighted, whoſe Wounds, and whoſe Love, cry for Vengeance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt. <hi>3.</hi>
               </label> What wilt thou be able to ſay for thy ſelf at laſt, if thou art without Chriſt? Come, Sinner! thou canſt talk, and be as unconcerned at preſent as any Man. Thou dareſt, it may be now, to ſcorn Chriſt, ridicule and make ſport at his moſt ſolemn and affectionate Entreaties, and revile thoſe his Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, who would perſwade thee to cloſe with his gracious Offers. But this is not the way to Heaven: When thou ſhalt appear before the great Tribunal
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:43210:71"/>of the moſt Juſt and Holy God, thou wilt not dare to repeat any of thy op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrious reproachful Expreſſions, thou wilt not be able to juſtify thy contemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt. Their ſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will be very dreadful, who ſhall be left to plead their own Cauſe at the great Day of Judgment. Be as great and daring as thou wilt at preſent, know thou, that more potent and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Perſons than thy ſelf, will then be covered with ſhame, be full of conſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and horror, and not dare to open their Mouths in their own vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Didſt thou never read nor hear of thoſe great and powerful, wealthy and honourable, couragious and valiant Ones, who ſhall call to the Mountains to fall on them, and the Hills to cover them, from the Face and Wrath of the Lamb? <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.15, 16, 17.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt. <hi>4.</hi>
               </label> What wilt thou think of Chriſt, and what wilt thou be willing to give for an Intereſt in Chriſt, at the approach
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:43210:71"/>of Death, and when thou muſt come before the Judgment of the Great God? If Chriſt will be precious and deſirable when thou ſeeſt Death and Hell naked before thee, certainly he ought to be precious to thee at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Thou doſt not know how ſoon Death may arreſt thee, how ſoon thou mayſt lie under its ſtroak; within how few Days or Hours God may ſay to thee, Come, Sinner, give up thy Account! O, Sinner, whoever thou art, be thy Thoughts what they will at preſent, yet if thou hadſt Worlds, yea, thouſands of Worlds at thy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal, thou wouldſt gladly and freely give and part with them all at the great Day of Judgment, for the leaſt ſaving Intereſt in Chriſt. O, Sinner! doſt thou know what it is to leave the World with Sin and Guilt cleaving to thy Soul? Doſt thou know what it is to die, and enter into Eternity, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having thy Peace made with God? Doſt thou know what it is to ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Tribunal of an unreconciled God, and to have Chriſt appear againſt thee, demanding full Juſtice againſt
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:43210:72"/>thee, for thy ſtubborn, refractory, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuous deſpiſing of Him, and his often tendred rich Grace?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt. <hi>5.</hi>
               </label> What Reflections have thoſe who are now in Hell, on their having ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chriſt, and ſtubbornly ſtood out againſt all his Entreaties? Do any of thoſe things which they preferred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Chriſt, when they were on Earth, afford them any real comfort? Have they any abatement of their Pain and Torment, by remembring that they purchaſed ſuch Pleaſures, or amaſſed to themſelves ſuch Treaſures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting and refuſing to comply with the gracious Offers the Son of God did make to them? Alas, their remembring of theſe things, doth inflame Hell the more; this makes Damnation more than ordinarily terrible; this makes the ſight of God and Chriſt amazing and dreadful to the utmoſt degree. To conſider they ſold God and Chriſt, their Souls, and Heaven, and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for ſuch Trifles, ſuch periſhing
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:43210:72"/>and unſatisfying things, is beyond all imagination penetrating and afflicting. O! couldſt thou ſee the Damned in their Chains, and didſt thou hear their ſhreiks and howlings; or wouldſt thou but conſider how their miſery and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſs is heightned and increaſed by their deſpiſing and making light of Chriſt? What thoughts wouldſt thou entertain! how dreadful wouldſt thou apprehend the rejecting of Chriſt to be, when he makes his gracious Viſits, and pleads and expoſtulates with Sinners for admittance? What thoughts wouldſt thou have, didſt thou hear thoſe miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and helpleſs Wretches crying out, O the Saviour that we did ſlight! O the Salvation we did neglect! O the Offers of Grace and Mercy we did wickedly and contemptuouſly caſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind our backs! O the many, the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, the importunate, the affectionate and loving entreaties and courtings of the Son of God, which we did ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornly reſiſt, and offer the moſt unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable and wicked deſpite unto! O, it is this, this, that makes our Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thus out of meaſure, to exceed
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:43210:73"/>and tranſcend theirs, who were never in a capacity of ſinning at our rate! 'Tis this that makes Hell ſo hot and glowing to us, that ſinks us ſo much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low all others in this bottomleſs Pit! O, what would theſe do, might they have the Offers which thou refuſeſt to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of? How would they rejoice, how ſpeedily, gladly, and heartily would they cloſe with Chriſt, might they have an offer of Grace, Pardon, and Mercy made once more to them!</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt. <hi>6.</hi>
               </label> Doſt thou think that any of thoſe who have received Chriſt in ſincerity, did ever repent of their ſo doing? It is our ignorance of Chriſt, and unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintedneſs with him, that makes us think ſo lightly of him. Did we but taſte and know how good the Lord is; had we but the ſame ſenſe, experience, and knowledge of his Excellencies they have, who do indeed admit him into their Hearts, we ſhould have the like Love, Zeal, and Affection for him which they have. Thoſe who have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:43210:73"/>him, do rejoice in and love him: They account him the only Joy of their Hearts, they eſteem him their Portion, their All, and their only Good. Have not thoſe who, for the ſake of Chriſt, have been expoſed to all kind of Sufferings, Hardſhips, and ill Uſages in the World rejoiced in the ſame? Have not they found the ſatisfactions accruing to them, from the Faithfulneſs and Love of Chriſt, ſo exceeding great, and full of inexpreſſible ſweetneſs and comfort, they have almoſt overlook'd, they have really thought all the Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of this Life very little and inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, eſpecially when Faith in Chriſt hath mounted and carried their Souls to take a view and proſpect of what Chriſt will hereafter advance them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18. Gold and Silver, Crowns, and Earthly Kingdoms, are of no value, more vile and contemptible than the Dung and Mire of the Streets, when made uſe of to bribe and hire one that has received Chriſt into his Heart, to fall off from him and reject him. I have ſerved Chriſt (ſaid <hi>Polycarp</hi>) fourſcore and ſix Years, and he never
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:43210:74"/>did me any harm; and do you think (ſaid he to thoſe who would have bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed and perſwaded him to renounce Chriſt) that now I will renounce and blaſpheme, and diſhonour my King and Saviour? Do you think the glorified Saints are ſorry they choſe and received Chriſt? Why, they can every jot as eaſily be weary of Heaven, as repent of their entertaining ſuch a Gueſt.</p>
            <p>Now do thou exerciſe thy Thoughts about theſe things with the greateſt ſeriouſneſs, and anſwer theſe Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions diſtinctly and impartially unto thy Conſcience, and preſs on thy Soul ſuch Conſiderations as thou findeſt have the greateſt tendency to ſtartle, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken and move thee, that thou mayſt not continue under the dreadful guilt of ſlighting Chriſt, and rejecting the gracious Motions he doth make thee of his Love. And, O that I knew what Words would excite thy drowſy Soul, and what Arguments would influence and make ſome kind of impreſſions on thy Mind, Affections, and Heart? I would urge them for thy good, with all
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:43210:74"/>the life and fervency that is poſſible. Conſider, Sinner, doth the Son of God condeſcend to plead and argue with thee for thy Benefit and Comfort? This is a very wonderful thing indeed; the Heavens may well be called to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, and the Earth to give ear; ſuch a prodigy of Love may make impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions on the very Mountains and Rocks. And what, wilt thou ſtill reſiſt his Courtings, and be the more contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, by how much the more importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate he is with thee? O, how juſtly may we call to the Heavens to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhed, and the Earth to be horribly afraid, at the manifeſtation of ſuch ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity and ingratitude? How will all the Creatures, inanimate, and ſenſleſs things, upbraid ſuch ſottiſh ſturdineſs! and finally bear witneſs, and give in evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence againſt it?</p>
            <p>But, alas, after all, what ſignifies the Diſcourſe of a poor Mortal? <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon</hi> found, by experience, that he had reaſon to ſay, <hi>The old Man, in the Hearts of Sinners, was too ſtrong for young</hi> Melancthon. It is not
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:43210:75"/>in the Miniſter's Power to reach the Heart. But Glorious, Almighty, and moſt Gracious God, thou art above all, and thou canſt ſpeak to the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and overcome the moſt perverſe and ſtubborn Heart; thou canſt, and doſt ordinarily make thy Strength and power to appear, in the weakneſs of thy meaneſt Servants: Lord, to thee we turn, and of thee we beg, that that Power and Plenty of thy good Spirit may be ſent forth, that poor Sinners may not walk in darkneſs, and be held any longer in bondage by Satan and their Luſts, but that they now may caſt away from them their Idols, may yield up themſelves to Chriſt in the ſincerity of their Hearts, and not oppoſe and reſiſt him any longer. Lord, do thou look down in thy Power and Strength; and do thou mightily perſwade and prevail on the Hearts of thoſe who have hitherto ſtood out againſt the Calls and Entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of their Saviour! exert thy Power, ſtretch forth thy mighty Arm, deſcend in the abundance of thy Grace, and bring thy Word and Exhortations to
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:43210:75"/>Peoples Souls and Conſciences, with thy ſpecial Efficacy, and then ſhall People hear thy Son's Voice, and knock, and open unto him.</p>
            <p>Now, Sinner, if thou art at all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with any of theſe Conſiderations, and doſt truly deſire to receive Chriſt into thy Heart; I will conclude all I have at this time to ſay unto thee, by propoſing a few Directions for thy help, and aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <label>I.</label> Labour to get a deep affectionate ſenſe of thy own inſufficiency, empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and miſery without Chriſt. Study the Law of God, how ſtrict and pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual it is! How many Duties are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, how many Sins forbid; what Curſes and Judgments threatned; how weak and impotent thou art; how far the Law is from either communicating Strength, or providing thee a Pardon: How powerful and ſevere infinite Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is; how liable thou art, and this upon innumerable accounts, to all the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:43210:76"/>Vengeance and Horror infinite Juſtice can inflict: How dreadful, how miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, how helpleſs thy ſtate is without a Mediator! Think on theſe things till thou art throughly ſenſible of thy need of Chriſt; and how impoſſible it is for thee to eſcape any other way than by Chriſt. We need Chriſt to preſent our beſt Services to God, and obtain them acceptance with the Father. O, what need have we then of Chriſt, to ſave us from our manifold Sins, and from the direful Puniſhments they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Luke</hi> 15.21. Chriſt will be welcome indeed, when we truly ſee our need of him.</p>
            <p>
               <label>II.</label> Strive to get thy Heart cleanſed from every thing which is contrary to Chriſt, and hath a tendency to keep him out of thy Heart. Get every Sin imbittered to thy Soul, that thou mayſt hate eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing which is an Enemy to Chriſt. Oppoſe Chriſt to every Luſt, and ſinful ſtirring of Heart; harbour no Luſt nor Sin in thy Heart, fight againſt Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations;
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:43210:76"/>learn to overcome Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Sins, by reviving in thy Mind the oppoſition and enmity there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Chriſt and Sin; curb and check, mortify and ſubdue every ſinful Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, by alleadging againſt it, Thou art an Enemy to my Saviour! to allow and entertain thee, would be to fight againſt Chriſt. O, I will not for a World do any thing that may offend and diſpleaſe the Son of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>III.</label> Pray earneſtly that the Spirit of God may mould and form thy Heart into a right frame and temper for Chriſt. When a Prince comes to take up his reſidence at any Place, or Houſe, it is not only neceſſary that the Lug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, and Lumber, and Filth, be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved and caſt out of Doors, but that all places be righted up, and have their proper Furniture: So when Chriſt comes to take up his abode with us, we are not only to caſt away our Luſts and Sins, but our Hearts muſt be fitted and diſpoſed to receive him, by the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:43210:77"/>Operation of his Holy Spirit, beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying and enriching them with Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Heavenly Qualifications. And therefore it will concern us to be ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt in our Prayers, that the good Spirit of God may come down upon us, and make our Hearts and Souls meet Temples for the Son of God to dwell in.</p>
            <p>
               <label>IV.</label> Go forth unto Chriſt, by the actings of Faith upon all occaſions. <hi>Let Chriſt dwell in your Hearts by Faith,</hi> Epheſ. 3.17. according to every alteration in your condition; and according to all the diverſities of Providence do you look unto Chriſt, exerciſe Faith on him, and by Faith fetch ſupplies of Grace from him.</p>
            <p>
               <label>V.</label> Meditate much and often on the Love of Chriſt to Sinners. Read over the Goſpel, the ſeveral Apoſtolical Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and the many Prophecies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:43210:77"/>Chriſt, eſpecially <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63. take notice of the many remarkable Paſſages there, relating to Chriſt, declaring his Condeſcention and Love, weigh them ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, and preſs them upon thy own Soul and Conſcience, dwell on theſe Matters in thy Thoughts, and expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late with thy ſelf about them. What, hath the Son of God taken my Nature! has the King of Glory condeſcended to live here in the form of a Servant! did he patiently undergo all the unjuſt Affronts and Contempts of lewd and prophane People! did he bear the weight of God's Wrath, and actually lay down his Life in the moſt open, ſcandalous, curſed, linguering, and painful kind of Death then known in the World, and was all this for my ſake! O, incomprehenſible Love! What ſhall I return unto my Saviour for all this? I can never love Chriſt enough; may I never ceaſe admiring the many Inſtances wherein his Love hath broke forth unto me; may I ſo wonder at, and be affected with all theſe things, that love to Chriſt may ſhine through all the paſſages of my
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:43210:78"/>Life: May I never be at reſt, till I do arrive at the full enjoyment of my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour in his own Kingdom. What, has the Lord Jeſus Chriſt done ſo much for me! has he revealed ſuch Truths, made ſuch Promiſes, ſuffered ſuch Sorrows, ſubmitted to ſuch a Death, as are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in the Holy Scriptures? are ſo many glorious and wonderful Things related concerning him? Doth he now reign in Heaven, and hath he purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſuch bleſſed Inheritance, and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Treaſures for poor Sinners? Nay, doth he ſtill importune and entreat me to accept of Him and his Benefits! God forbid that I ſhould oppoſe his Motions, and reſiſt his Love any longer. Shall the King of Glory be ſlighted and excluded ſtill by me? Shall I wilfully caſt away my own Soul, and ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neglect this great Salvation? God forbid. Shall it be writ on my Grave, Here lies the ſturdy ungrateful Wretch, that did wilfully reſiſt Jeſus Chriſt; the Wretch that reſolved to force his way to Hell, through all the Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Diſcouragements, infinite Juſtice, and infinite Mercy had laid in
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:43210:78"/>his way? that vile unpitiable Miſcreant, that would damn himſelf in ſpite of Love it ſelf?</p>
            <p>
               <label>VI.</label> Converſe much with thoſe who are experienced Chriſtians, and have much acquaintance with Chriſt. <hi>He that walketh with wiſe Men, ſhall be wiſe; but a Companion of Fools ſhall be deſtroyed,</hi> Prov. 13.20. Such People will very much aſſiſt thee in thy cloſing with Chriſt, by their Diſcourſes, Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Practice. They can tell thee ſuch things concerning Chriſt, from their own experience, as will warm and melt thy Heart, and inflame thy Affections. They will contribute much to thy help by their advice and counſel, by the accounts they can give thee off their own experiences, by their watchfulneſs over thee, and by their fervent effectual Prayers for thee.</p>
            <pb n="136" facs="tcp:43210:79"/>
            <p>
               <label>VII.</label> Labour to be acquainted with, and to obſerve all the Motions and Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Chriſt towards Sinners, and cloſe with, and improve every one of them, when he is pleaſed to exert any of them towards thy ſelf. Take notice of the Calls he doth give thee in his Word, and the awakening viſits he doth make thee by his providential Occurrences, and improve theſe to put thee on a more diligent ſearch, and cloſe walking after him; and to excite and quicken in thee more fervent deſires after Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with him.</p>
            <p>
               <label>VIII.</label> Conſcientiouſly frequent thoſe Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances wherein Chriſt hath promiſed his more eſpecial Preſence. Prepare thy ſelf carefully to meet thy Lord, and come with paſſionate Deſires, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident Expectations, grounded on his Faithfulneſs, Word, and Promiſe, that he will exhibit himſelf unto thoſe
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:43210:79"/>Souls, that ſincerely long and wait for him.</p>
            <p>
               <label>IX.</label> Laſtly; Faithfully reſign and give up thy ſelf to Chriſt. When thy Heart is affected truly with a ſenſe of Chriſt's Love, then deſire him, by fervent Prayer, that he will be pleaſed to take thee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Covenant with himſelf, and make a hearty, faithful, entire reſignation of thy ſelf unto him. O, Bleſſed Jeſus, moſt Holy Saviour! I am unworthy I acknowledg to make uſe of thy Name; I have often reſiſted and ſinned againſt thy conſtraining Love, but I am hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily ſorry now that ever I did ſo! O, compaſſionate and tender-hearted Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, reject not an humble, returning, mourning Penitent; embrace me, the unworthieſt of all others in the Arms of thy Mercy, and admit me into thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour; the more ſtubborn, and head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrong, and wilful I have been, the more abundantly let thy Grace be manifeſted toward me, and bring me under the more powerful influences of thy Love. Lord, ſeize, by the Power of thy Grace,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:43210:80"/>and take poſſeſſion of this Soul: Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Saviour, whoſe Bowels have ever yearned over the miſerable, and who haſt been always compaſſionate and gracious to the unworthy, favourably accept of this poor Oblation: Lord, it is the purchaſe of thy own Blood; O, reject not, deſpiſe not, caſt not away what thou haſt bought at ſo dear a rate. Lord, here is my Soul, my Body, my Heart, my Affections, my Mind, my Judgment, my Will: Lord, here is all that I have; Lord, I reſign up all unto thee, without any reſervation; do with all, as pleaſeth thee beſt, only accept of them: O Lord, I love thee above all, I deſire, with my whole Soul, to love thee every Day more and more. Lord, dwell in my Heart, rule over my whole Man, bring all my Powers unto a true and ſound ſubjection unto, and compliance with thee in every thing: May my Soul always admire thee, my Heart love thee, my Tongue praiſe thee, my Lips ſpeak of thy Glory and Goodneſs: May my Life glorify thee; may I in every part of my practice, ſerve and honour thee; may all my
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:43210:80"/>Faculties and Members be ready and faithful Servants for, and unto thee. Lord, I long to be with thee, my Soul panteth after thee. <hi>For me to live is Chriſt, and to die is gain,</hi> Phil. 1.21.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
